<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caueat for commen cursetors vvlgarely called uagabones, set forth by Thomas Harman, esquier, for the vtilite and proffyt of hys naturall countrey. Newly agmented and imprinted Anno Domini. M.D.LXUII. Vewed, examined and allowed, according vnto the Queenes Maiestyes iniunctions</title>
            <author>Harman, Thomas, fl. 1567.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1567</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847736</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847736</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 464:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caueat for commen cursetors vvlgarely called uagabones, set forth by Thomas Harman, esquier, for the vtilite and proffyt of hys naturall countrey. Newly agmented and imprinted Anno Domini. M.D.LXUII. Vewed, examined and allowed, according vnto the Queenes Maiestyes iniunctions</title>
                  <author>Harman, Thomas, fl. 1567.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestret at the signe of the Faulcon by Wylliam Gryffith and are to be solde at his shoppe in Saynt Dunstones Churche yarde. in the West,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[M.D.LXUII] [1567]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First known edition. On D2 verso Harman says the first edition was partly printed by 1 November 1566; on G4 verso he calls the present item: "this second impression". Imprint date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A caveat for cursetors.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ G⁶.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at top affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rogues and vagabonds --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Caueat <hi>FOR COMMEN CVR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>SETORS VVLGARELY CALLED</hi> Vagabones, ſet forth by Thomas Harman. Eſquier, for the vtilite and proffyt of hys naturall Countrey. Newly agmented and Imprinted Anno Domini. M.D.LXVII.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Vewed, examined and allowed, according vnto the Queenes Maieſtyes Iniunctions</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of two beggars or vagrants with a horse and cart and a small dog, accompanied by two uniformed men or soldiers with whips</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>IMPRINTED</hi> at London in Fleteſtret at the ſigne of the Faulcon by Wylliam Gryffith and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe in Saynt Dunſtones Churche yarde. in the Weſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a besom or bunch of twigs, a stick or staff, and some rope or string, all separate</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Thre thinges to be noted </l>
               <l>all in their kynde,</l>
               <l>A ſtaff, a beeſom, and </l>
               <l>with, that wyll wynde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ A beeſome of byrche, for babes verye fyt,</l>
               <l>A longe laſtinge iybbet for loubbers as meete,</l>
               <l>A wyth to wynde vp, that theſe wyll not keepe,</l>
               <l>Bynde all vp in one, and vſe it to ſweepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a broom, composed of a besom or bunch of twigs, a stick or staff, and some rope or string, bound together</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12796:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the ryght honorable and my ſingular good Lady. <hi>Elizabeth Countes of Shrewſbury. Thomas Harman wiſheth all ioye</hi> and perfite felicitie here and in the worlde to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S of Auncient and longe tyme, there hath bene and is now at this preſent many good godly profitable lawes and actes made and ſet forthe in this moſte noble and floryſhynge realme, for the reliefe, ſuccour, comforte and ſuſtentacion of the poore nedye impotente and my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerable creatures, beinge and in habiting in all parts of the ſame. So is there (righte honorable and myne eſpecyall good Lady) moſt holſom eſtatutes, ordinances and neceſſary lawes, made ſetforth and publiſhed for the extreme puniſhement of all vagaran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſturdy vacabons, as paſſeth throughe and by all parts of this famous yle moſt ydelly and wyckedly, And I wel by good experience vnderſtandinge and conſideringe your moſt tender, pytyfull, gentle and noble nature, not onelye hauinge a vygelant and mercifull eye to your poore indygente and feable pariſhnores, yea not onely in the pariſhe where your honour moſt happely doth dwell, but alſo in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, inuyroninge or nighe adioyninge to the ſame. As alſo aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly powrynge out dayly your ardent and bountifull charytie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all ſuch as commeth for reliefe vnto your luckely gates.</p>
            <p>I thought it good, neceſſary, and my bounden dutye to acquaynte your goodnes with the abhominable, wycked and deteſtable behauor of all theſe rowſey, ragged rabblement of rakehelles, that vnder the preſence of great miſery, dyſeaſes and other innumerable calamites whiche they fayne through great hipocriſye do wyn and gayne great aimes in all places where they wyly wander, to the vtter deludinge of the good geuers, deceauinge and impoueriſhing of all ſuche poore houſholders both ſicke and ſore, as nether can or maye walke abroad for reliefe and comforte (where in dede moſt mercy is to be ſhewed.) And for that I (moſt honorable Lady) beinge placed as a poore gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman haue kepte a houſe theſe twenty yeares, where vnto pouerty daylye hath and doth repayre, not without ſome releife as my poore callinge and habylytie maye and doth extende: I haue of late yeares gathered a great ſuſpition that all ſhould not be well, and as the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerbe ſaythe <hi>(ſome thinge lurke and laye hyd that dyd not playnely apeare)</hi> for I hauinge more occation throughe ſickenes to tarye and remayne at home, then I haue bene accuſtomed do by my there abyding, talke
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12796:3"/> and confere dayly with many of theſe wyly-wanderars of both ſorts as well men and wemen, as boyes and gyrles: by whom I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and vnderſtande, their depe diſſimulation and deteſtable dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, beinge maruelous ſuttle and craftye in there kynde, for not one amongſt twentye wyll diſcouer either declare there ſcelorus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets: yet with fayre flatteringe wordes, money, and good chere, I haue attained to the typ by ſuch as the meaneſt of them hath wandred theſe xiii yeres and moſt xvi, and ſome twenty and vpwarde, and not withoute faythfull promeſſe made vnto them neuer to diſcouer their names or any thinge they ſhewed me: for they woulde all ſaye yf the vpright men ſhould vnderſtand thereof they ſhould not be onlye gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſlye beaten, but put in danger of their lyues by the ſayde vpright men. There was a fewe yeres ſince a ſmall breefe ſet forthe of ſome zelous man to his countrey of whom I knowe not, that made a lytle ſhewe of there names and vſage, and gaue a glymſinge lyghte not ſufficient to perſwad of their peuyſhe peltinge and pickinge practy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but well worthy of prayſe. But (good madame) with no leſſe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell then good wyll, I haue repayred and rygged the Shyp of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and haue hoyſſed vp the ſayles of good fortune, that ſhe maye ſafelye paſſe aboute and through all partes of this noble realme, and there make porte ſale of her wyſhed wares, to the confuſion of their drowſeye demener, and vnlawfull languag, pylfring pycking, wily wanderinge, and lykinge lecherye, of all theſe rablement of raſcales, that raunges about all the coſtes of the ſame. So that their vndecent dolefull dealing and excerable exerſices, maye apere to all as it were in a glaſſe, that therby the Iuſticers and Shréeues may in their cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes, be more vygelant to puniſhe theſe malefactors, and the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables Bayliffes, and boſholders ſettinge aſyde all feare, ſlouthe, &amp; pytie, maye be more circomſpecte in executing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the aforeſayde Iuſticers. Then wyll no more this raſcall rabbleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t raunge about the countrey, then greater releife maye bée ſhewed to the pouertye of eche paryſhe, then ſhall we kepe our Horſſes in oure paſtures vnſtolen, then our lynnen clothes ſhall and maye lye ſafely one our hedges vntouched, then ſhall wee not haue our clothes and lynnen hoked oute at oure wyndowes as well by daye as by nyght. Then ſhall we not haue our howſes broken vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night, as of late one of my nyghtbors had and two great buckes of clothes ſtolen out, and moſt of the ſame fyne Lynnen. Then ſhall wee ſafely kepe oure pygges and poultrey from pylfringe. Then ſhall we ſurely paſſe by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12796:3"/> the hyghe wayes leading to marketes and fayres vnharmed. Then ſhall our Shoppes and bothes be vnpycked and ſpoyled. Then ſhall theſe vncomly companies bee diſperſed and ſet to labour for their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, or haſtely hange for their demerites. Then ſhall it incourag a great number of gentlemen and others ſeinge this ſecuritie, to ſet vp houſes and kepe hoſpitalyty in the countrey, too y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comfort of their nighboures, releife of the poore, &amp; to the amendemet of the common-welth. Then ſhall not ſinne and wyckednes ſo much abound among vs. Then wyll gods wrathe be much thee more pacified towards vs. Then ſhall we not taſte of ſo many and ſoundry plages, as now day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly raygneth ouer vs. And then ſhall this Famous Empyre, bee in more welth and better floryſhe, to the ineſtymable ioye and comfort of the Quenes moſte excellent maieſtye whome god of his infynyce goodnes to his great glory long and manye yeares make moſte proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſly to raygne ouer vs to the great Felycity of all the Peres and Nobles, and to the vnſpeakable ioye releife and quietnes of mind of all her faythfull Commons and Subiectes. Nowe me thinketh I fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe theſe peuyſhe peruerſe and peſtilence people begyne to freate, fume, ſweare and ſtare at this my booke, their lyfe being layd open and aparantly paynted out that their confuſion and end draweth one a pace Where as in dede if it be well wayed it is ſet forthe for their ſynguler profyt and commoditie, for the ſure ſafegarde of their lyues here in this world, that they ſhorter not the ſame before their tyme, and that by their true labour and good lyfe, in the world to com they maye ſaue their Soules, that Chryſt the ſeconde perſon in Trinitye hath ſo derely bought with his moſt precious bloud: ſo that hereby I ſhall do them more good the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they could haue deuiſed for them ſelues. For beholde their lyfe beinge ſo manyfeſt wycked and ſo aparantlye knowen, the honorable wyll abhore them. The worſhipfull wyl re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte them, the yemen wyll ſharpely tawnte them, The Huſbande men vtterly defye them, The Laborynge men bluntly chyde them, The wemen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a loud reclamation wonder at them. And all Chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with clapping handes crye out at them, I many tymes muſinge with my ſelfe at theſe myſcheuous miſliuers merueled whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they toke their oryginall and begynning, howe longe they haue exerciſed their exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable wandring a bout. I thought it meete to confere with a verye olde man that I was well acquaynted with, whoſe wit and memory is meruelous for hys yeares, being about the age of foureſcore, what he knew when he was yong of theſe louſey leuterars. And he ſhewed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12796:4"/> me that when he was yong, he wayted vpon a man of much worſhip in Kent, who died immediatly after the laſte Duke of Buckingham was beheaded, at his buryall there was ſuche a number of beggers beſides poore houſholders dwellinge there aboutes that vnneth they myghtly or ſtand about the Houſe: then was there prepared for them a great and a large barne, and a great far ore ſod out in Furmentye for them, with bread and drinke aboundantly to furneſh out the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, and euery perſon had two pence for ſuch was the dole. When Night approched y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore houſholders repaired home to their houſes, the other wayfaring bolde beggers remayned all night in the barne, and the ſame barne beinge ſerched with light in the night by this old man and then yonge, with others, they tolde ſeuen ſcore perſones of men, euery of them hauinge his woman, except it were two wemen that lay alone to gether for ſome eſpecyall cauſe. Thus hauing their makes to make mery with all, the buryall was turnede to bouſynge and belly chere, morning to myrthe, faſtinge to feaſtinge, prayer to paſtyme, and preſſinge of papes, and lamenting to Lechery. So that it maye apere this vncomly company hath had a longe continuance, but then nothinge geuen ſo much to pylferinge, pyckinge and ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge, and as far as I can learne or vnderſtand by the examination of a nomber of them, their languag, which they terme peddelars Fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che or cantig began but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in theſe .xxx. yeres lytle aboue, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the firſt inuenter therof was hanged, all ſaue the heade, for that is the fynall end of them all, or els to dye of ſome filthy and horible diſeaſes: but much harme is don in the means ſpace by their continuance, as ſome x. xii. and xvi yeres before they be conſented, and the nomber of them doth dayly renew. I hope their ſynne is now at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt, and that as ſhort and as ſpedy a redres wyl be for theſe, as hath bene of late yeres for the wretched, wily wanderinge vagabondes, calling and naming themſelves Egiptians, depely diſſemblings and longe hydinge and coueringe their de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe deceitfull practiſes, fedinge the rude common people wholy addicted and geuen to nouelites, ioyes, and newe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, delytinge them with the ſtrangenes of the attyre of their heades, and practiſinge paumiſtrie to ſuche as woulde knowe their fortunes. And to be ſhort all theues and hores, as I may well wryt, as ſome haue had true experience, a nomber can well wytnes, and a great ſort hath woll felte it. And now (thankes bee to god) throughe wholſome lawes and the due execution thereof, all be diſperſed, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, &amp; the memory of then cleane extynguyſhed, that when they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12796:4"/> bee once named hereafter, our Chyldren wyll muche maruell what kynde of people they were: and ſo I truſt ſhal ſhortly happen of theſe. For what thinge doth chiefly cauſe theſe rowſeye rake helles thus to continue and dayly increaſe? ſurely a nomber of wycked parſons that keepe typlyng Houſes in all theres, where they haue ſuccour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and what ſo euer they bryng they are ſure to receaue money for the ſame, for they ſell good penyworthes. The byers haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt gayne, yea yf they haue nether money nor ware they wylbe truſted, their credite is much. I haue taken a note of a good manye of them &amp; wylſend their names and dwelling places to ſuch Inſtecers as dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth nere or next vnto them, that they by their good wiſedomes maye diſplace the ſame, and auctoryſe ſuch, as haue honeſty. I wyl not blot my boke with their names, becauſe they be reſident. But as for this fletinge Fellowſhyp I haue truly ſetforth the moſt part of them that be doers at this preſente with their names that they be knowene by. Alſo I haue placed in the end thereof their leud langage callinge the ſame pedlers Frenche or canting. And how ſhall I end my prologe, makinge true declaration (right honorable Lady) as they ſhall fall in order of their vntymelye tryfelinge time, leud lyfe, and pernitious practiſes, truſtinge that the ſame ſhall neyther trouble or abaſh your moſt tender, tymerous and pytifull Nature, to thinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmall méede ſhould growe vnto you for ſuch Almes ſo geuen. For god our marci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and moſt louinge father well knoweth your hartes and good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, the geuer neuer wanteth his reward, accordinge to the ſaying of Saynt Auguſtyn: as there is (neyther ſhalbe) any ſynne vnpuniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, euen ſo ſhall there not be eny good dede vnrewarded. But how comfortably ſpeketh Chryſt our Sauiour vnto as in his goſpel (geue ye and it ſhalbe geuen you agayne) behold farther, good Madam that for a cup of colde water, Chryſt hath promiſed a good reward. Now ſaynt Auſten properly declareth why Chryſt ſpeaketh of cold water, becauſe the pooreſt man that is, ſhall not excuſe him ſelfe from that cherytable warke leaſt he would paraduenture ſaye that he hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wood, poot nor pan to warme any water with. Se farther what god ſpeaketh in the mouth of his prophete Eſaye, breake thy bread to him that is a hongred, he ſayth not geue him a hole loſe: for parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the poore man hath it not to geue, then let him geue a pece. This much is ſayd becauſe the poore that hath it ſhould not be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nowe howe much more then, the riche? Thus you ſee good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. for your treaſure here diſperſed where nede and lacke is, it ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12796:5"/> be heaped by aboundantlye for you in heauen, where neyther ruſt or moth ſhal corupt or deſtroy the ſame. Vnto which tryumphant place after many good happy, and fortunat yeres proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſlye here diſpended, you may for euer and euer there moſt ioyfully remayn. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.
<figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a female figure with a book on a lectern</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12796:5"/>
            <head>¶ The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough good Reader I wright in plain termes and not ſo playnly as truely, concerning the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaning honeſtly to all men, and wyſhe them as much good as to myne owne harte, yet as there hathe bene ſo there is nowe, and hereafter wylbe, curyous heds to finde fauttes, wherefore I thought it neceſſary now at this ſeconde Impreſſion to acquaynt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with a great faulte as ſome takethe it, but none as I meane it, callinge theſe Vagabonds Curſetors in the intytelynge of my booke as runneres or rangers aboute the countrey, deriued of this Laten word <hi>(CVRRO)</hi> neither do I wryght it Cooreſetores with a duble do or Cowreſetors with a w which hath ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſingnification, is there no deuerſite betwen a gardein and a garden, maynteynaunce, &amp; maintenance, Streytes and ſtretes, thoſe that haue vnderſtanding knowe there is a great dyfference, who is ſo ingnorant by theſe dayes as knoweth not the meaning of a vagabone, and yf an ydell leuterat ſhould ſo be called of eny man, would not he thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k it bothe odyous and reprochefull, wyll he not ſhonne the name? ye and where as he maye and dare, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bent browes wyll reueng that name of Ingnomy, yet this playne name vagabone is deryued as others be of Laten wordes, and now vſe makes it commen to al men, but let vs loke back four. C. yeres ſithens, &amp; let vs ſe whether this playn word vagabon was vſed or no, I beleue not and why, becauſe I rede of no ſuch name in the old eſtatutes of this realme, vnles it be in the margente of the booke, or in the Table, which in the collection and pryntinge was ſet in, but theſe were then the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men names of theſe leud leuterares Fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores, Robardeſmen, Drawlatches, &amp; valyant beggares, yf I ſhould haue vſed ſuche wordes or the ſame drder of wryting as this realme vſed in kynge Henry the thyrd or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12796:6"/> Edward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſtes time, Oh what a groſe barberous fellow haue we here his wryting is both homely and darke that wee had nede to haue an interpretar, yet then it was verye well and in ſhort ſeaſon a great change we ſee well this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycat age ſhall haue his tyme on the other ſyde, eloquence haue I none, I neuer was acquaynted with the muſes, I neuer taſted of Helycon. But accordinge to my playne or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I haue ſetforth this worke ſymplye and truelye, with ſuch vſual words and termes as is among vs wel known and frequented. So that as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouerbe ſaythe (all though truth be blamed it ſhal neuer be ſhamed) well good reader I meane not to be tedyous vnto the, but haue added fiue or ſixe more tales becauſe ſome of them weare donn whyle my booke was fyrſte in the preſſe, and as I truſte I haue deſerued no rebuke for my good wyll, euen ſo I deſyre no prayſe for my payne coſt and trauell. But faythfullye for the proffyt and benyfyt of my countrey, I haue don it, that the whole body of the Realme may ſe and vnderſtand their leud lyfe and pernitious practiſſes that all maye ſpedelye helpe to amend that is amyſſe, Amen ſaye all with me.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.
<figure>
                  <figDesc>knotwork ornament or design</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="type">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12796:6"/>
            <head>¶ A Ruffler</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Rufflar becauſe he is firſt in degre of this odious order. And is ſo called in a ſtatute made for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Vacabonds. In the xxvii yeare of Kyng Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eight late of moſt famous memory. Hee ſhalbe, firſte placed as the worthieſt of this vnruly rableme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And he is ſo called when he goeth firſt abroade eyther he hath ſerued in the warres, or els he hath bene a ſeruing man and weary of well doing, ſhakinge of all payne, doth chuſe him this ydle lyfe, and wretchely wanderes about the moſt ſhyres of this realme. And with ſtout Adaſcite, demaundeth where he thinketh hee maye bee bold, and circomſpecte ynough as he ſethe cauſe to aſke charitie, rufully and lamentably, that it would make a flyntey hart to relent. and pitye his miſerable eſtate, howe he hath bene maymed and brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the warres, &amp; parauenture ſome wyll ſhew you ſome outward wounde, whiche he gotte at ſome dronken fraye, eyther haltynge of ſome preuye wounde feſtred with a fylthy firy flankard. For be well aſſured that the hardiſt ſouldiers be eyther ſlayne or maymed, eyther and they eſcape all haſſardes, and retourne home agayne, if they bee without reliefe of their friends, they wyll ſurely deſperatly robbe, and ſteale, and eyther ſhortlye be hanged or miſerablye dye in pryſon, for they be ſo much aſhamed and diſdayne to beg or aſke charity, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they wyll as deſperatly fight for to lyue &amp; mayntayn them ſelues as manfully, and valyantly, they ventered them ſelues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prynces quarell. Nowe theſe Rufflars the oute caſtes of ſeruinge men when begginge or crauinge fayles, then they pycke and pylfer from other inferiour beggers, that they meete by the way as Roages, Pallards, Mortes, and Dores. Yea if they meete with a woman alone ridinge to the market, eyther olde man or boye, that he well knowethe wyll not reſiſte, ſuch they filche and ſpoyle. Theſe rufflares after a yere or two at the fartheſt become vpryght men, vnles they be preuented by twinde hempe. ¶ I had of late yeres an old man to my tennant, who coſtomably a great tyme went twiſe in the weeke to London, eyther with fruite or with peſcods, when tyme ſerued therefore. And as hee was comming homeward on blacke heath, at the end thereof next to ſhotars hyll he ouer tooke two rufflars the one manerly wayting on the other as one had ben the mayſter, &amp; the other the man, or ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12796:7"/> caryinge his maſteres cloke, this olde man was verye glad that bee might haue their company ouer the hyl, becauſe that day he had made a good market, for hee had ſeuen ſhyllinges in his purſe, and a nolde angell, which this poore man had thought had not bene in his purſe, for hee wylled his wyfe ouer nyght to take out the ſame angell, and laye it vp vntyll his comminge home agayne. And he verely thought that his wyfe had ſo don, whiche in deede for gott to do it. Thus after ſalutations, had this maiſter rufflar entered into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication with this ſimple old man, who rydinge ſoftlye beſide them, commoned of many matters. Thus fedinge this old man with pleaſaunt talke, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll they were one the toppe of the hyll, where theſe rufflares mighte well beholde the coaſte aboute them cleare. Quiclye ſtepes vnto this poore man, and taketh holde of his horſe brydell, and leadeth him in to the wode, and demaundeth of him what and how much monye he had in his purſe. Now by my troth quoth this old man you are a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye gentle man, I knowe you meane not to take awaye anye thinge from me, but rather to geue me ſome if I ſhoulde aſke it of you. By and by this ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thyefe caſteth the cloke that he caryed on his arme about this poore manes face, that he ſhould not marke or vew them, with ſharpe words to delyuer quicly that he had and to confeſſe truly what was in his purſe. This poore man then all abaſhed yelded, and confeſſed he had but iuſt ſeuen ſhylinges in his purſe and the trouth is he knew of no more. This old angell was falen out of a lytle purſe into the botome of a great purſe. Now this ſeuen ſhyllings in white money they quickly found, thinkinge in dede that there had bene no more, yet farther groping and ſearchinge, found this old angell. And with greate admiration this gentleman thiefe begane to bleſſe hym ſaying, good lorde what a whorlde is this, howe maye (quoth hee) a man beleue or truſte in the ſame, ſe you not (quoth he) this old knaue tolde me that he had but ſeuen ſhyllings, and here is more, by an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, what an old knaue and a falſe knaue? haue we here quoth this rufflar, oure lorde haue mercy on vs, wyll this worlde neuer be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and there with wente their waye. And lefte the olde man in the wood doinge him no more harme. But ſorowfully ſighinge this olde man returning home declared his miſaduenture, with all the words and circomſtaunces aboue ſhewed. Whereat for the tyme was great laughing, and this poore man for his loſſes among his louing neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures well conſidered in the ende.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Vpright man.</head>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12796:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Vpright man the ſecond in ſecte of this vnſemly ſorte muſt be next placed, of theſe rainging rablement of raſſcales ſome bee ſeruing men, artificers, and laboryng men, traded vp in huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry. Theſe not minding to get their lyuing with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwet of their face, but caſting of all payne wyll wander after their wycked maner, through the moſt ſhyres of this realme, as Sommerſet ſhyre, Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyre, Barkeſhyre, Oxfordeſhyre, Harfordeſhyre, Middilſex, Eſſex, Suffolke, Northfolke Suffex, Surrye, and Kente, as the cheife and beſt ſhyres of reliefe. Yea not with out puniſhment by ſtocks, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, and impriſonment, in moſt of theſe places, aboue ſayde. Yet not withſtanding they haue ſo good lyking in their lewnd, lecherous loytering, that full quicly all their puniſhmentes is forgotten. And repentance is neuer thought vpon, vntyll they clyme thre tres with a ladder. Theſe vnrewly raſcales in their roilyng, diſperce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, into ſeuerall companyes, as occation ſeruethe, ſometyme more and ſomtime leſſe. As yf they repayre to a poore huſbandmans houſe, he wyll go alone or one with him, and ſtoutly demaund his charity, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhewing how he hath ſerued in the warres, and their maymed, eyther that he ſeketh ſeruice, &amp; ſayth he would be glad to take payn, for his lyuing, although he meaneth nothinge leſſe. Yf he be offered any meate or drynke, he vtterly refuſeth ſcornefully, and wyl naught but money, and yf he eſpye yong pyggs or pultry, he well noteth the place and the the next nyght or ſhortly after hee wyll be ſure to haue ſome of them; which they brynge to their ſtawlinge kens, which is their typpling houſes, as well knowen to them according to the olde prouerbe (as the begger knowes his diſhe.) For you muſt vnderſtand euery Typpling ale houſe wyll neyther receiue them or their wares but ſome certayne houſes in euery ſhyre, eſpecially for that purpoſe, where they ſhalbe better welcome to them, then honiſter men. For by ſuch haue they moſt gayne, and ſhalbe conuayde eyther into ſome loft out of the waye, or other ſecret corner not commen to any other, and thether repayre, at accuſtomed tymes, their harlots which they terme Mortes, and Doxes, not with emty hands, for they be as ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in picking, riffling &amp; filching, as the vpryght men, and nothinge inferior, to them in all kynd of wyckednes, as in other places hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they ſhalbe touched. At theſe foreſayde pelting peniſh places and vnmannerly, metings O how the pottes walke about, their talki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tounges talke at large. They howle and bowſe one to another, and for the tyme houſing belly there. And after there ruyſting recreation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12796:8"/> yf there be not rome ynough in the houſe they haue cleane ſtrawe in ſome barne or backehouſe nere adioyning where they couch comly to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, and it were dogge, and byche, and he that is hardyſte maye haue his choyſe, vnleſſe for a lytle good maner ſome wyll take there owne that they haue made promyſe vnto, vntyll they be out of ſight, and then according to the old adage (out of minde.) Yet theſe vpright men ſtand ſo much vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their reputation, as they wyll in no caſe haue their wemen walke with them, but ſeperat them ſelues for a tyme, a moneth or more. And mete at fayres, or great markers where they mete to pylfer and ſteale, from ſtaules, ſhoppes, or bothes. At theſe fayres the vpryght men, vſe commonly to lye, &amp; lingar in hye wayes by lanes. ſome prety way or diſtaunce from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place, by which wayes they be aſſured that compeny paſſeth ſtyll, two and fro. And ther the wyll demaund with cap in hand and comly curteſy, the deuotion and charity of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people. They haue ben much lately whipped at fayrs. Yf they aſke at a ſtout yemans, or farmars houſe his charity, they wyll goe ſtrong as thre or foure in a company. Where for feare more then good wyll, they often haue reliefe, they ſyldome or neuer paſſe by a Iuſtices houſe, but haue by wayes, vnleſſe he dwell alone and but weakelye manned thether wyll they alſo go ſtronge after a ſlye ſuttle forte, as with theire armes bounde vp with ketcher or lyſte, hauinge wrapte about the ſame filthy clothes, either their legges in ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner bewrapped halting down right, Not vnprouided of good codgels which they cary to ſuſtayne them, and as they fayne to keepe dogges from them, when they come to ſuch good gentlemens houſes Yf any ſearche be made or they ſuſpected for pyltring clothes, of hedgges, or breaking of houſes, which they commonly do, when the owners bee eyther at the market, church, or other wayes occupyed aboute their buſines, eyther robbe ſome ſely man or woman by the hye waye, as many tymes they do. Then they hygh them into wodes, great thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and other ruffe corneres, where they lye lurkinge thre or foure dayes to gether, and haue meate and drinke brought them by theyre Mortes, and Dores, and whyle they thus lye hydden in couert in the night they be not ydle, nether as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common ſaying is (wel occupyed) for then as the wyly foxe crepinge out of his den ſeketh his praye for pultery ſo do theſe for lynnen and any thinge els worth money, that lyeth about or nere a houſe. As ſomtyme a whole bucke of clothes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed awaye at a tyme. When they haue a greatter bootye then they maye cary awaye quickly to their ſtawling kendes as is aboue ſayd.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12796:8"/> They wyll hyde the ſame for a thre dayes in ſome thicke couert, and in the night time carye the ſame lyke good water Spanlles to their foreſayd houſes, to whom they wyll diſcouer. Where or in what pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they had the ſame, where the markes ſhalbe picked out cleane, &amp; conuayde craftelye face of to ſell. If the man or woman of the houſe want money the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. If theſe vpright men haue nether money nor wares, at theſe houſes they ſhalbe truſted for their vitales, and it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, to twentye or thirty ſhyllinges. Yea if it fortune any of theſe vpright men to be taken either ſuſpected or charged with felonye, or petye brybrye, don at ſuch a time or ſuch a place, he wyll ſaye he was in his hoſtes houſe. And if the man or wyfe of that houſe be examined by an officer, they boldelye vouche that they lodged him ſuche a time whereby the truth cannot appeare. And if the chaunce to be retayned into ſeruice through their lamentable words, with any welthy man. They wyll tary but a ſmale tyme, either robbing his maiſter, or ſom of his fellowes. And ſome of them vſeth this polocye, that although they trauayle into al theſe ſhyres, aboue ſaid, yet wyl they haue good credite eſpiciallye in one ſhyre where at diuers good farmars houſes they be well knowen where they worke a month in a place or more &amp; will for that time behaue them ſelues very honeſtlye and paynfully. And maye at any tyme for their good vſage haue worke of them and to theſe at a ded lyft or laſte refuge they maye ſafely repayre vnto and be welcome. When in other places for a knacke of knauery that they haue playd thei dare not tary. Theſe vpright men wil ſildom or neuer want, for what is gotten by anye Mort, or Doxe, if it pleaſe him hee doth comaunde the ſame. And if he mete anye begger whether hee be ſturdye or impotent he wyll demaunde of him whether euer he was ſtalled to the roge or no. If he ſaye he was, he wyll knowe of whom and his name y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtalled hym. And if he be not learnedly able to ſhewe him the whole circumſtaunce therof he wyl ſpoyle him of his money, eyther of his beſt garment if it be worth any money, and haue him to the bowſing ken. Which is to ſome typpling houſe next adioyninge and laieth their to gage the beſt thing that he hath for twenty pence or two ſhyllinges, this man obeyeth for feare of beating. Then doth this vpriight man call for a gage of bowſe whiche is a quarte pot of drinke and powres the ſame vpon his pelde paie adding theſe words. I. G. P. do ſtalle thée W. T. to the Roge, and that from hence forth it ſhall be lawefull for the to cante, that is to aſke or begge, for thy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in al places. Here you ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vpright man is of great auctoriti
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12796:9"/> For all ſorts of beggers, are obedient to his heſts, and ſermounteth all others in pyltring, and ſtealinge. I latly had ſtanding in my wel houſe which ſtandeth on the backeſide of my houſe, a greate cawdren of copper being then full of water, hauinge in the ſame halfe a doſon of pewter dyſhes, well marked, and ſtamped with the connizance of my armes, which being well noted when they were taken out were ſet a ſide the water powred out, and my caudren taken away, beinge of ſuche bygnes that one man vnleſſe he were of greate ſtrength was not able farre to carye the ſame. Not withſtanding the ſame was one night within this two yeares conuayed more then halfe a myle from my houſe, into a common or heth. And ther beſtowed in a great fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhe. I then immediatly the next day ſent one of my men to Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and there gaue warning in Sothwarke, kent ſtreete, and Barmeſey ſtréete to all the Tynckars there dwelling. That if any ſuch caudorn came, thether to be ſold, the bringar therof ſhould be ſtayed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed twenty ſhyllinges for a reward. I gaue alſo intelligence to the water men that kept the ferres that no ſuch veſſell ſhoulde be eyther conuayd to London, or into eſſex promiſing the lyke reward, to haue vnderſtanding therof. This my doing was well vnderſtand in many places, about, and that the feare of eſpyinge ſo troubled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſcience of the ſtealer, that my caudorendaye vntouched in the thicke firbuſhe more then halfe a yeare after which by a great chaunce was found by hunteres for conneys, for one chaunced to runne into the ſame buſhe where my caudren was and being perceaued one thruſt his ſtaffe into the ſame buſhe and hyt my caudren a great blowe the ſound whereof dyd cauſe the man to thinke and hope that there was ſome great trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure hidden, wherby he thought to be the better whyle he lyued. And in farther ſearching he found my caudren, ſo had I the ſame agayne vnloked for.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Hoker or Anggicar.</head>
            <p>THeſe hokers or Angglears be peryllous and moſt wicked knaues, and be deryued or procede forth from the vpright men they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menly go in freſe ierkynes and gally ſlopes poynted bene the the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kne, theſe when they practiſe there pylfringe it is all by night for as they walke a day times from houſe to houſe to demaund charite thei vigelantly marke where or in what place they may attayne to there praye, caſting there eyes vp to euery wyndow wel noting what they ſe their, whether apparell, or linnen, hanginge nere vnto the ſayde windowes and that wyl they be ſure to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next night folowing,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12796:9"/> for they cuſtomably carry with them a ſtaffe of .v. or .vi. foote long, in which within one ynch of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tope there of is a litle hole bored through in which hole they putte an yron hoke and with the ſame they wyll plucke vnto them quicly any thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may reche ther with, which hoke in the day tyme they couertly cary aboute them, &amp; is neuer ſene or taken oute till they come to the place where they worke ther fete, ſuch haue I ſene at my houſe and haue oft talked with them and haue handled ther ſtaues not then vnderſtanding to what vſe or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they ſerued, although I hadde and perceiued by there talke and behauiour great lykelyhode of euyll ſuſpition in them, they wyll ether leane vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon there ſtaffe to hyde the hole thereof when they talke with you, or holde their hande apon the hole and what ſtuffe either wollen or lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen they thus hoke out they neuer carye the ſame foorthwith to their ſtaulyng kens, but hides the ſame a .iii. daies in ſome ſecret corner, &amp; after conueyes the ſame to their houſes aboueſaid, where their hoſt or hoſtys geueth them money for the ſame, but halfe the value that it is worth, or els their doxes ſhall a farre of ſell the ſame at the like hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. I was credebly informed that a hoker came to a farmers houſe in the ded of the night and putting backe a drawe window of a low cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, the bed ſtanding hard by the ſayde wyndowe, in which laye .iii. parſones a man and two bygge boyes, this hoker with his ſtaffe pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of their garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which lay vpon them to kepe them warme with the couerlet and ſhete and lefte them lying a ſlepe naked ſauing there ſhertes, and had away all cleane, and neuer could vnderſtande where it became. I verely ſuppoſe that when they wer wel waked with cold they ſurely thought that Robin goodfelow (accordinge to the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) had bene with them that night.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Roge.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Roge is neither ſo ſtoute or hardy as the vprightman. Many of them will go fayntly, and looke piteouſly, when they ſee, either meete any perſon, hauing a kercher as white as my ſhooes tyed aboute their heade, with a ſhort ſtaffe in their hand, halting, although they neede not, requiri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g almes of ſuch as they meete, or to what houſe they ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e. But you may eaſely perceiue by their colour, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they cary both health and hipocriſie about them, whereby they gette gaine, when others want that cannot fayne and diſſemble. Others there be that walke ſturdely about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, &amp; faineth to ſeke a brother or kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his, dwelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in ſom part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhire, either y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath a letter to
<pb facs="tcp:12796:10"/> to delyuer to ſom honeſt houſholder, dwelling out of an other Shyre, and wyll ſhewe you the ſame fayre ſealed, wyth the ſuperſcription to the partye he ſpeaketh of, becauſe you ſhall not thinke him to runne ydelly about the countrey, ether haue they this ſhyfte, they wyl ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a cirtificate or paſport about them from ſom Iuſticer of the peace, with his hand and ſeale vnto the ſame, howe hee hath byne whipped and puniſhed for a vacabonde according to the lawes of this realme, and that he muſte returne to. T. where he was borne or laſt dwelt, by a certayne daye lymited in the ſame, whiche ſhalbe a good longe daye. And all this fayned, bycauſe without feare they woulde wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly wander, and wyll renue the ſame, where or when it pleaſeth them: for they haue of their affinity that can well wryte and reade. Theſe alſo wyll picke and ſteale as the vpright men, and hath their women and metinges at places appoynted, and nothing to them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour in all kynde of knauery. There be of theſe Roges Curtales wearing ſhorte clokes, that wyll chaunge their apparell, as occaſion ſerueth. And their end is eyther hanging, which they call trinninge in their language, or die meſerably of the pockes. ¶ There was not longe ſithens two Roges that alwaies did aſſociate them ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and would neuer ſeperate themſelues vnles it were for ſome eſpecial cauſes, for they were ſworne brothers, and were both of one age and much like of fauour, theſe two traueling into eaſt kent reſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnto an alehouſe there beinge weried with traueling, ſalutinge with ſhort curtſey when they came into the houſe ſuch as they ſawe ſitting there, in which company was the parſon of the pariſh and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge for a pot of the beſt ale, ſat downe at the tables ende, the likor liked them ſo wel that they had pot vpon pot, and ſometime for a litel good maner would drinke &amp; offer the cup to ſuch as they beſt fancied, &amp; to be ſhort they ſat out al the company, for eche man departed home about their buſines. When they had wel refreſhed themſelues, then theſe rowſy roges requeſted the good man of the houſe with his wife to ſit downe and drinke with them of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they inquired what prieſt the ſame was &amp; where he dwelt, then they feyninge that they had an vncle a prieſt, and that he ſhould dwel in theſe partes, which by al pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumptions it ſhould be he, &amp; that they came of purpoſe to ſpeake with him, but becauſe they had not ſene him ſithens they were ſixe yeres old, they durſt not be bold to take acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of him vntil thei were farder inſtructed of the turth, &amp; began to enquire of his name, &amp; how long he had dwelt there, &amp; howe farre his houſe was of from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12796:10"/> they were in, the good wife of the howſe thinkinge them honeſt men without diſceit becauſe they ſo farre enquired of their kinſeman was but of a good zelous naturall intent, ſhewed them cherefully that he was an honeſt man &amp; welbeloued in the pariſh and of good wealth, &amp; had ben there reſident .xv yeres at the leaſt, but ſaith ſhe are you both brothers, yea ſurely ſaid they, we haue bene both in one belly &amp; were twinnes, mercy god ꝙ this foliſh woman it may wel be for ye be not much vnlike and wente vnto her hall windowe callinge theſe yong men vnto her and loking out thereat pointed with her fingar &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed them the howſe ſtanding alone no howſe nere the ſame by almoſt a quarter of a mile, that ſaith ſhe is your vncles howſe, nay ſaith one of them he is not onely my vncle but alſo my godfather, it may well be ꝙ ſhe, nature wil binde him to be the better vnto you, wel ꝙ they we be weary and meane not to trouble our vncle to night, but to mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe god willinge we will ſee him and do our duty, but I praye you doth our vncle occupy huſbandry what company hath he in his howſe alas ſaith ſhe but one old woman &amp; a boy, he hath no occupying at al, tuſhe ꝙ this good wife you be mad men go to him this night for he hath better lodging for you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue, &amp; yet I ſpeake foliſhly againſt my own profit, for by your tarying here I ſhould gayn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more by you now by my troth ꝙ one of them we thanke you good hoſtes for your holſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, &amp; we meane to do as you wil vs, we wil pauſe a while and by that time it wilbe almoſt night, and I praye you geue vs a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening, ſo manerly paying for that they toke bad their hoſte &amp; hoſtes farewel with taking leaue of the cup, marched merely out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dores towards this parſons houſe vewed the ſame wel round about &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by two bowſhots of into a yong wodde where thei lay conſulting what they ſhould do vntil midnight, ꝙ one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſharper wit &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiller then the other to his fellowe thou ſeeſt that this houſe is ſtone walled about, and that we cannot wel breake in in any parte therof, thou ſeeſt alſo that the windowes be thicke of mullions that there is no krepinge in betwene, wherefore we muſt of neceſſity vſe ſome po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licy when ſtrength will not ſerue, I haue a horſe lock here about me ſaith he &amp; this I hope ſhal ſerue our turne, ſo when it was about .xii. of the clock they came to the houſe and lurked nere vnto his chamber window, the dog of the houſe barked a good, that with the noiſe this prieſt waketh out of his ſlepe &amp; bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cough &amp; hem, then one of theſe roges ſteps forth nerer the window &amp; maketh a ruful &amp; pitiful noyſe, requiring for Chriſt ſakes ſome reliefe that was both hongry &amp; thirſty
<pb facs="tcp:12796:11"/> and was like to lye without the dores all nighte and ſtarue for colde vnles he were releued by him with ſome ſmall pece of money, wher dwelleſt thou quoth this parſon, alas ſir ſaith this roge I haue ſmal dwelling &amp; haue come out of my way, and I ſhould nowe ſaith he go to any towne nowe at this time of nighte, they woulde ſet me in the ſtockes and puniſhe me, well quoth this pitifull parſon, away from my houſe either lye in ſome of my our houſes vntill the morning and holde here is a couple of pence for thee, a god rewarde you quoth this roge and in heauen may you finde it. The perſon openeth his wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe and thruſteth out his arme to geue his almes to this Roge that came whining to receiue it, and quickly taketh holde of his hand and calleth his fellowe to him which was redye at hande with the horſe locke and clappeth the ſame about the wreſt of his arme that the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lions ſtanding ſo cloſe together for ſtrength, that for his life he could not plucke in his arme againe, and made him beleue vnles he would at the leaſt geue them .iii. li. they would ſome of his arme fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy. So that this poore parſon in ferre to loſe his hande called vp hys olde woman that lay in the loft ouer him, and willed her to take out all the money he had, which was .iiii. markes which he ſaide was all the money in his houſe for he had lent vi. li. to one of his neighbours not iiji. daies before wel or they, maſter perſon if you haue no more, vpon this condicion we wil take of the locke that you will drinke .xii. d. for our ſakes to morowe at the alehouſe where we founde you and thank the good wife for the good chere ſhe made vs, he promiſed faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully that he woulde ſo do, ſo they toke of the locke &amp; went theyr way ſo farre ere it was daye, that the parſon coulde neuer heue any vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding more of them, nowe this parſon ſorowfully ſlombering that night betwene feare and hope, though it was but folly to make two ſorrowes of one, he vſed contentacion for his remedy, not forgettyng in the morning to performe his promiſe but we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betims to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour that kept tiplinge and aſked angerly where the ſame two men were that dranke with her yeſter daye, which two men ꝙ this good wife? the ſtraungers that came in when I was at your houſe wyth my neighbors yeſterday, what your neuewes ꝙ ſhe, my neuewes ꝙ this parſon I trowe thou art mad, nay by god ꝙ this good wife as ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber as you, for they tolde me faithfully that you were their vncle, but in faith are you not ſo in dede, for by my trouth they are ſtrangers to me, I neuer ſaw them before. O out vpon them ꝙ the parſon they be falſe theues &amp; this nigut they compelled me to geue them all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12796:11"/> in my houſe. Benedicite ꝙ this good wife &amp; haue they ſo in dede as I ſhall aunſwere before god one of them tolde me beſides that you were godfather to him and that he truſted to haue your bleſſinge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he departed, what did he quoth this parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a halter bleſſe him for me, me thinketh by the maſſe by your countenance you loked ſo wild<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you came in quoth this good wife that ſome thing was amis, I vſe not to geſte quoth this parſon when I ſpeake ſo earneſtly, why all your ſorrowes goe with it quoth this good wife, and ſitte downe here and I wil fil a freſhe potte of ale ſhall make you mery againe, ye ſaith this parſon fill in and geue me ſome meate for they made me ſweare and promiſe them faithfully that I ſhoulde drynke .xii.d. with you thys daye, what dyd they quoth ſhe now by the mary maſſe they be mery knaues, I warraunte you they meane to bye no lande wyth your money, but howe coulde they come into you in the night youre dores beinge ſhutte faſt, your houſe is verye ſtronge, then this parſon ſhewed her all the hole circumſtaunce howe he gaue them his almes oute at the wyndows, the made ſuche lamentable crye that it pytyed hym at the harte, for he ſawe but one when he putte out his hand at the windowe, be ruled by me quoth this good wyfe, wherein quoth this parſon, by my trouthe neuer ſpeake more of it, when they ſhall vnderſtande of it in the paryſhe they will but laugh you to ſkorne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>A Wylde Roge</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Wilde Roge is he that is borne a Roge, he is more ſubtil and more geuen by nature to all kinde of knauery, then the other, as beaſtely begotten in barne or buſhes, and from his infancy traded vp in trechery, yea and before ripenes of yeares doth permit, wallowinge in lewde lechery, but that is counted amongeſt them no ſin. For this is their cuſtome that when they mete in barne at night euery one getteth a make to lye wythall, &amp; there chaunce to be twen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye in a companye, as there is ſometyme more, and ſometyme leſſe: for to one man that goeth abrode, there are at the leaſte two women, which neuer make it ſtraunge when they be called, although ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knewe him before. Then when the day doth appeare, he rouſes him vp and ſhakes his eares, and awaye wanderynge, where he may gette oughte to the hurte of others. Yet before he ſkyppeth oute of hys couche and departeth from his darling, if he like her well he will
<pb facs="tcp:12796:12"/> appoint her where to mete ſhortly after, with a warninge to worke warely for ſome chetes, that their meting might be the merier. Not long ſithens a wild roge chaunced to meete a pore neighbour of mine who for honeſty and good nature ſurmounted many. This pore man tiding homeward fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> London, where he had made his market, this roge demaunded a peny for gods ſake to kepe him a true man. This ſimple man beholding him wel, &amp; ſawe he was of taule perſonage w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good quarter ſtaffe in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, it much pitied him as he ſaid to ſe him want, for he was wel able to ſerue his prince in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wars. Thus being moued with pity, &amp; lokt in his purs to finde out a peny &amp; in loking for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, he plucked out .viii.s. in white mony, &amp; raked therin to finde a ſingle peny &amp; at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt finding one doth offer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to this wild roge, but he ſeing ſo much mony in this ſimple mans hand, being ſtriken to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart with a couetous deſier, bid him forthwith deliuer al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had, or els he would with his ſtaffe beate out his braynes. For it was not a peny wold nowe que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch his thirſt thus ſwalowing his ſpitle gredely down, ſpoiled this pore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mony y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had, &amp; lept ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hedge into a thick wood, and went his way as merely, as this good ſimple man came home ſorowfully. I once rebuking a wild roge becauſe he wente idly about: he ſhewed me that he was a begger by enherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, his Graundfather was a begger, his father was one, &amp; he muſt nedes be one by good reaſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Prygger of Prauncers.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Prigger of Prauncers be horſe ſtealers, for to prigge ſignifieth in their language to ſteale, &amp; a Prauncer is a horſe, ſo beinge put together the matter is plaine. Theſe go commonly in Ier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins of leather or of white freſe, &amp; carry little wandes in their hands, and will walke through grounds and paſturs, to ſearch and ſe horſes mete for their purpoſe. And if thei chaunce to be met and aſked by the owners of the grounde what they make there, they fayne ſtraighte that they haue loſte theyr waye, and deſyre to be enſtructed the beſte way to ſuche a place. Theſe will alſo repayre to gentlemens houſes and aſke theyr charitye, and will offer theyr ſeruice, And if you aſke them what they can doe, they wil ſaye that they can kepe two or thre Geldinges, and waite vppon a Gentleman. Theſe haue alſo theyr women, that walkinge from them in other places, marke where and what they ſee abrode, and ſheweth theſe Priggars therof, when they meete, whych is wythin a weeke or two. And loke where they ſteale
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12796:12"/> any thynge, they conuey the ſame at the leaſte three ſcore miles of or more. There was a Gentleman a verye friende of myne, rydynge from London homewarde into Kente, hauinge within three myles of his houſe buſyneſſe, alyghted of his horſe, and hys man alſo, in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye village, where diuers houſes were, and looked about hym where he myghte haue a conuenyent perſon to walke his horſe, becauſe he would ſpeak w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a Farmer, that dwelte on the backe ſide of the ſayde village, little aboue a quarter of a myle from the place where he ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and had his man to waight vpon hym, as it was mete for his cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge: eſpieng a Priggar there ſtanding, thinkinge the ſame to dwel there, charging this prity prigginge perſon to walke his horſe well, and that they might not ſtande ſtill for takynge of colde, and at his re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turne (which he ſaide ſhould not be longe) he would geue him a peny to drinke, and ſo wente aboute his buſines. Thys peltinge Priggar proude of his praye, walketh hys horſes vp and downe, till he ſawe the Gentleman out of ſighte, and leapes him into the ſaddell, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye he goeth a mayne. This Gentleman returning, and findyng not his horſes, ſente his man to the one ende of the village, &amp; he went himſelf vnto the other ende, and enquired as he went for hys horſes that were walked and began ſomewhat to ſuſpecte, becauſe neither he nor his man coulde neyther ſee nor fynde him. Then this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man diligently enquired of three or foure towne dwellers there whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther any ſuch perſon, declaring his ſtature, age, apparel, with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye linamentes of his body as he coulde call to remembraunce. And <hi>vna voce</hi> all ſayde that no ſuch man dwelte in their ſtreate, neither in the pariſh that they knewe of, but ſome did wel remember that ſuche a one they ſawe there lyrkinge and huggeringe two houres before the Gentleman came thether and a ſtraunger to them. I had thought quoth this Gentleman he had here dwelled, and marched home ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly in his botes, farre from the place he dwelt not I ſuppoſe at his comming home he ſente ſuch wayes as he ſuſpected or thought mete to ſearch for this Prigger, but hetherto he neuer harde any tidinges againe of his palfreys. I had the beſt gelding ſtolen out of my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture that I had amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt others while this boke was firſt a printing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A pallyarde</head>
            <p>THeſe Palliards be called alſo Clapperdogens, theſe go with pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched clokes, &amp; haue their Morts with them, which they cal wiues and if he goe to one houſe to aſke his almes, his wife ſhal goe to
<pb facs="tcp:12796:13"/> another, for what they get, as bread, cheefe, malte, and well, they ſel the ſame for redy money, for ſo they get more, and if they went toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, although they be this deuided in the daie, yet they mete iompe at night. Yf they chaunce to come to ſome gentylmans houſe ſtandinge alone, and be demaunded whether they be man and wyfe, &amp; if he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that any doubteth therof he ſheweth them a Teſtimonial with the miniſters name and others of the ſame pariſhe, naminge a pariſhe in ſome ſhere, fare diſtant from the place where he ſheweth the ſame. This writing he carieth to ſalue that ſore. There be many Iriſhe men that goe about with cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfeate licenſes, and if they perceiue you wyl ſtraytly examen them, they will immediatlie ſaie they can ſpeake no Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>Farther, vnderſtand for trouth that the worſt and wickedſt of all this beaſtly generation are ſcarce comparable to theſe prating Pally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes, All for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part of theſe wil either lay to their legs an herbe called Sperewort, eyther Arſnicke, which is called Rateſbane. The nature of this Spereworte wyll rayſe a great bliſter in a night vpon the ſoundeſt part of his bodye, &amp; if the ſame be taken away it wyl drie vp againe and no harme. But this Arſnicke will ſo poyſon the ſame legge or ſore, that it will euer after be incurable this do they for gayn and to be pitied. The moſt of theſe that walke about be walchmen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Frater.</head>
            <p>SOme of theſe Fraters will cary blacke boxes at their gyrdel, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in they haue a brief of the Queenes maieſties letters patentes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to ſuch a poore ſpitlehouſe for the reliefe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore ther. which briefe is a coppie of the letters patentes, &amp; vtterly fained, if it be in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or parchement without the great ſeale. Alſo if the ſame brief be in print, it is alſo of auctoritie. For the Printers wil ſee, &amp; wel vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d before it come in preſſe, that the ſame is lawfull. Alſo I am credibly in formed, that the chiefe Proctors of many of theſe houſes, that ſeldome trauel abrode the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, but haue their factors to gather for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which looke very ſlenderly to the impotent &amp; miſerable creatures committed to their charge; &amp; die for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of cheriſhing, wheras they &amp; their wiues are well cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med &amp; clothed, &amp; will haue of the beſt. And the founders of euery ſuch houſe, or the chiefe of the pariſhe wher they be, would bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſee vnto theſe Proctors, that they might do their duty, they ſhould be wel ſpoken of here, and in the world to come abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantly therefore rewarded. I had of late an honeſt man, and of good wealth, repayred to my houſe to common wyth me about certeyne affaires. I inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12796:13"/> the ſame to dinner, and dinner being done, I demanded of him ſome newes of thoſe parties were boe dideſt. Thankes be to God ſyr (ſayth be) al is wel &amp; good now. Now (quoth I) this ſame now declareth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome things of late hath not bene wel. Yes ſyr (qd. he) matter is not great, I had thought I ſhould haue bene well beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within this ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th night. How ſo (quoth I) Mary ſir ſayd he, I am Conſtable for fault of a better, and was commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to watch. The watch being ſet, I toke an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one of my neighbors with me, and went vp to the end of the town as far as the ſpittle houſe, at which houſe I heard a great noyſe, &amp; drawing nere ſtode cloſe vnder the wall, and this was at one of the clocke after mydnight. Where he hard ſwearing, prating, and wagers laying, and the pot a paſe walki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, and .xl. d. gaged vpon a matche of wraſtling, pitching of the barre, and caſting of the ſledge. And not they go in a fuſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fume into the backe ſyde, wher was a great Axiltrye, and thei fell to pitching of the barre, being iii to iii. The Moone dyd ſhine bright, the Conſtable with his neighbour might ſee and beholde all that was done. And howe the wife of the houſe was roſting of a Pyg, while her geſtes wer in their matche. At the laſt they could not agree vpon a caſt, and fel at wordes, and frome wordes to blowes. The Conſtable with his fellow runnes vnto them to parte them, and in the parting lyrkes a drye blow or two. Then the noyſe increaſed, the Conſtable would haue had them to to the ſtocks. The wife of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes out w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the Conſtable for her geſtes, and leaues the Pyg at the fyre alone. In commeth tow or three of the next neighbours, being wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked with this noyſe, and into the houſe they come, and fynde none therin, but the Pygge wel roſted, and carieth the ſame away with them ſpyt and all, with ſuch bread and drinke alſo as ſtoode vpon the table. When the good man and the good wyfe of the houſe had intreated and pacified the Conſtable, ſhowing vnto him that they were Proctors and Factors all of Spyttlehouſes, and that they taryed there but to breake theyr faſt, and would ryde away imme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diately after, for they had farre to goe, and therfore ment to ride ſo earlye. And comming into theyr houſe againe, fynding the Pygge wyth bread and drincke all gonne, made a great exclamation, for they knewe not who had the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Conſtable returning and hearing the lamentable wordes of the good wyfe, how ſhe had loſt both meate, and drinke, and ſaw it was ſo in deede, he laughed in his ſleue, and commaunded her to dreſſe no more at vnlawful houres for any geſtes. For he thought
<pb facs="tcp:12796:14"/> better beſtowed vppon thoſe ſmell feaſtes his poore neighboures, then vppon ſuche ſturdye Lubbars. The nexte mornynge betimes the ſpitte and pottes were ſette at the Spittle howſe doore for the owner? Thus were theſe Factours begyled of theyr breakefaſte, and one of them had wel beaten an other, and by my trouth (quoth this Cunſtable) I was gladde when I was wel ryd of them. Why quoth I, could they caſte the barre and ſledge well? I wyll tel you ſyr (quoth he) you knowe there hathe bene many games this Som<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer, I thinke verely that if ſome of theſe Lubbars had bene there, and practyſed amongeſt others, I beleue they woulde haue carried awaye the beſte games. For they were ſo ſtronge and ſturdye, that I was not able to ſtande in their handes. Well (quoth I) at theſe games you ſpeake of, both legges and armes be tryed. Yea (quoth thys offycer they be wicked men. I haue ſene ſome of them ſithens wyth cloutes bounde aboute theyr legges, and haltyng wyth their ſtaffe in theyr handes. Wherefore ſome of theym (by GOD bee nought all.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Abraham man.</head>
            <p>THeſe Abraham men bee thoſe that fayne them ſelues to haue bene mad, and haue bene kept eyther in Bedleant, or in ſome other priſon a good tyme, and not one amongeſt twenty that euer came in pryſon for any ſuche cauſe: yet wyll they ſaye howe pitiouſly &amp; moſt extreamely they haue ben beaten &amp; dealte withal. Some of theſe be mery &amp; verye pleaſante, they wyl daunce &amp; ſyng, ſome others be as colde and reaſonable to talke wyth all. Theſe begge money, eyther when they come at Farmours howſes they wyll demaunde Baken, eyther cheeſe, or wooll, or any thinge that is worth money. And if they eſpy ſmal company within they will with fierce countenaunce demaunde ſomewhat. Where for feare the maydes wyll geue theym largely to be ridde of theym.</p>
            <p>If they maye conuenyently come by any cheate, they wyll pycke and ſteale, as the vprighte man or Roge, poultrey or lynnen. And al wemen that wander, be at theyr commaundements. Of all that euer I ſawe of thys kinde, one naming him ſelfe Stradling, is the craftieſt and moſte diſſemblingeſt Knaue. He is able wyth hys tounge and vſage to deceaue and abuſe the wiſeſt manne that is. And ſurelye for the proporcion of his bodie, with euerie member there vnto appertaininge, it cannot be amended. But as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12796:14"/> is (God hath done his part.) Thys Stradlyng ſaith hee was the Lord Sturtons man, and when he was executed, for very penſiuenes of mynde he fell out of hys witte, and ſo continued a yeare after and more, and that with the very greefe and feare he was taken wyth a marueilous palſey, that both head and handes will ſhake, when he talketh wyth any, and that apaſe or faſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by he is much pitied, and getteth greately. And if I had not deman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded of others both men and women, that commonly walketh as he doth, and knowen by them his deepe diſſimylation, I neuer hadde vnderſtand the ſame. And thus I ende wyth theſe kynde of vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>☞ A Freſh Water Mariner or Whipiacke.</head>
            <p>THeſe Freſh water Mariners their ſhipes were drowned in the playne of Saliſbury. Theſe kynde of Caterpillers counterfet great loſſes on the ſea, thoſe bee ſome Weſtern men, and moſt be Iryſh men. Theſe wyll runne about the country wyth a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet lycence, fayning either ſhipwracke, or ſpoyled by Pyrates neare the coaſt of Cornwall or Deuenſhire and ſet a land at ſome hauen towne there, hauyng a large &amp; formal writyng, as is aboue ſayd wyth the names &amp; ſeales of ſuch men of worſhippe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt iiii. or fiue as dwelleth neare or next to the place where thee fayne their landing. And nere to thoſe ſhieres wyll they not begge, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll they come into Wilſhire, Hamſhire, Barkſhire, Oxfordſhire, Harfordſhire, Middelſexe, and ſo to London, and downe by the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſeeke for their ſhippe and goodes that they neuer had, then paſſe they throughe Surrey, Soſſex, by the ſea coſtes, and ſort i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to Kent, demaunding almes to bring them home to theyr country.</p>
            <p>Some tyme they counterfet the ſeale of the Admiraltie. I haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers tymes taken awaye from them their licences of both ſortes, with ſuch money as they haue gathered, and haue confiſcated the ſame to the pouerty nigh adioyning to me. And they wyll not bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long without another. For at any good town they wil renew the ſame. Once with much threatning and faire promiſes I required to knowe of one company who made their licence. And they ſweare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they bought the ſame at Portſmouth of a Mariner there and it coſt him two ſhilinges, with ſuch warrants to be ſo good &amp; effectual, that if any of the beſt men of law or learned about Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſhould peruſe the ſame, they weare able to fynd no faute ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with but would aſſuredly allow the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:15"/>
            <head>¶ A counterfet Cranke.</head>
            <p>THeſe that do cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfet the Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke be yong knaues and yong harlots, that depely diſſemble the falling ſicknes. For the Cranke in their langage is the fallyng euyll, I haue ſeene ome of theſe with fayre writinges teſtimoniall, with the names and ſeales of ſome men of worſhip in Shropſhiere, and in other Shieres farre of, that I haue well knowen, and haue taken the ſame from them. Many of theſe do go without writinges, and wyl go halfe naked, and looke moſt pitiouſly. And if any clothes be geuen them, they immediately ſell the ſame, for weare it they will not, becauſe they would bee the more pitied, and weare filthy clothes on their heades, &amp; neuer go without a peece of white ſope about them, which if they ſee cauſe or preſent gaine, they wyl pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey the ſame into their mouth, and ſo worke the ſame ther, that they wyll fome as it were a Boore, &amp; marueilouſly for a time torment them ſelues, and thus deceiue they the common people, &amp; gaine much. Theſe haue commonly their harlots as the other.</p>
            <p>Apon Alhollenday in the morning laſt. Anno domini. 1566. or my my booke was halfe printed I meane the firſt impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther came early in the morninge a Counterfet Cranke vnder my lodgyng at the white Fryares within the cloyſter in a little yarde or coorte where abowtes laye two or three great Ladies beeng without the liberties of London wherby he hoped for the greater gayne, thys Cranke there lamentably lamenting and pytefully crying to be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leued declared to dyuers there hys paynfull and myſerable dyſeaſe I b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynge ryſen and not halfe ready harde his dolefull wordes and rufull mornings hering him name the falling ſycknes thought aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly to my ſelfe that he was a deepe deſembelar, ſo commynge owt at a ſodayn and beholding his ugly &amp; yrkſome attyre hys loth ſome &amp; horryble cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance it made me in a meruelous parplexite what to thinke of him whether it were fayned or trouth, for after this manner went he, he was naked from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waſt vpwarde ſauyng he had a olde gyrken of lether patched and that was looſe about hym that all his body lay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ote bare a fylthy fowle cloth he ware on hys hed being cut for the purpoſe hauing a narrow place to put owt his face wyth a bauer made to truſſe vp his beard and a ſtring that tyed the ſame downe cloſe abowte his neke wyth an olde felt hat whych he ſtyll caried in hys hand to receaue the cheryte &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of the people for that woulde he holde owte from hym ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12796:15"/> his face from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes downeward all ſmerde with freſh bloud as though he had new falen and byn tormented wyth hys paynful panges hys gyrken being all be rayde with durt and myre and his hatte and hoſen alſo as thoughe hee had wallowed in the myer, ſewrely the ſighte was monſtreous and terreble, I called him vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to me &amp; demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of hym what he ayled. A good maiſter quoth he I haue the greuous and painful dyſeas called the fallyng ſycknes why quoth I how commeth thy gyrken hoſe &amp; hat ſo be rayd wyth durt and myre &amp; thy ſkyn alſo. A good maſter I fel down on the backeſyde here in the fowle lane hard by the waterſyde and there I lay all moſt all night and haue bled all moſt all the bloud owte in my body, it raynd that morning very faſt and while I was thus talking with him a honeſt poore woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwelt therby brought hym a fayre lynnen cloth and bed hym wype his face therwith and there beyng a tobbe ſtandinge full of rayne water offered to gyue hym ſome in a diſhe that he might make hym ſelfe clene he refuſed the ſame why doſt thou ſo quoth I, a ſyr ſayth he yf I ſhuld waſhe my ſelfe I ſhould fall to bleeding a freſhe again and then I ſhould not ſtop my ſelfe, theſe wordes made me the more to ſuſpect hym.</p>
            <p>Then I aſked of him wher he was borne what is name was how long he had thys dyſeaſe &amp; what tyme he had ben here about Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in what place, ſyr ſayth he I was borne at Leyceſtar my name is Nicholas Gennins and I haue hadde this fallyng ſycknes .viii. yeares and I can get no remedy for the ſame for I haue it by kinde my father had it and my frendes before me, and I haue byne theſe two yeares here about London, and a yeare and a halfe in bethele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why waſt thou out of thy wyttes quoth I? ye ſyr that I was.</p>
            <p>what is the Kepars name of the howſe, hys name is quoth hee Iohn Smith, then quoth I hee muſt vnderſtande of thy dyſeaſe yf thou hadeſt the ſame for the tyme thou waſt there, he knoweth it well, ye not onely he but all the houſe beeſyde quoth thys Cranke for I came thens but within this fortnight, I hadde ſtande ſo long reaſoning the matter wyth him that I was a could and went in to my chamber and made me ready, and commaunded my ſeruant to repayre to bethelem and bring me trew word from the keper there whether any ſuch man hath bin with him as a priſoner hauing the dyſeaſe aforeſaid and gyue hym a not of hys name and the kepars alſo, my ſeruant retornyng to my lodgyng dyd aſſure me that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ther euer any ſuch man there nether yet any keper of any ſuche name, but he that was there keper he ſent me hys name in writinge affermynge that he letteth no man depart from hym vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:12796:16"/> he be ſet awaye by hys frendes and that none that came from hym beggeth abowte the City then I ſent for the Printar of thys booke, and ſhewed hym of thys dyſſembling Cranke and how I hadde ſent to Bethelem to vnderſtand the trough and what aunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were I receaued agayne requiring hym that I myght haue ſome ſeruant of his to watch him faithfully that day that I might vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand truſtely to what place he would repaire at night vnto, &amp; the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I promiſed to goe my ſelfe to ſee their order and that I would haue him to aſſociate me thether, he gladly graunted to my requeſt and ſent two boyes that both dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly and vigelantly accompliſht the charge geuen them and found the ſame Crank abowte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wher about the moſt parte of the daye he begged vnles it were about xii. of the clocke he went on the backſyde of Clementes. In without Temple barre there is a lane that goeth into the Feldes there he renewed his face againe wyth freſhe blud whych he cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aboute hym in a bladder and dawbed on freſhe dyrt apon hys gerken hat and hoſen.</p>
            <p>And ſo came backe agayne vnto the Temple and ſometyme to the Waterſyde and begged of all that paſſed hye, the boyes beeheld howe ſome gaue grotes, ſome ſyxe pens, ſome gaue more for hee looked ſo ouglei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and yrkſomlie that euerye one pytied hys myſerable caſe that beehelde hym, to bee ſhort there he paſſed all the daye tyll nyght approched, and when it began to bee ſomewhat darke he went to the waterſyde and toke a Skoller and was fette ouer the Water into Sainct Gorges feldes, contrarye to my expectation, for I hadde thought he woulde haue gonne in to Holborne or to Saynt Gylles in the felde but theſe boyes wyth (Argues and Lynces) eyes ſet ſewre watche vppon hym and the one toke a Bote and followed hym and the other went backe to tell hys maiſter.</p>
            <p>The Boye that ſo followed hym by Water, hadde no Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to paye for hys Bote hyre, but layde hys Penner and hys Ynkhorne to gage for a penny, and by that tyme the boye was ſet ouer, hys Maiſter with al celeryte hadde taken a Bote and follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed hym a paſe, now hadde they ſtyll a ſyght of the Cranke whych croſſed ouer the feldes towardes Newyngton and thether he went and by that tyme they came thether it was very darke, the pryntar hadde there no acquayntance nether any kynde of weapon about hym nether knew he how farre the Cranke woulde go, becawſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12796:16"/> he then ſuſpected that they dogged hym of purpoſe, he there ſtayed hym and called for the Conſtable which camforth diligently to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what the matter was thys zelous Printar charged thys offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer wyth hym as a malefacter and a deſſembelyng vagabonde, the Conſtable would haue layde him all nyght in the Cage that ſtode in the ſtreat, naye ſayth thys pytifull printer I pray you haue him into your houſe for this is lyke to bee a colde nyght and hee is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked you kepe a vytellynge houſe lette him be well cheryſhed thys nyght for he is well hable to paye for the ſame, I know well hys gaynes hath byn great to daye, and your howſe is a ſufficient pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the tyme &amp; we wyl there ſerche hym, the Conſtable agreed there vnto, they hadde him in, and cauſed him to waſhe hym ſelfe that donne they demaunded what money he hadde aboute hym, ſayth thys Cranke ſo God helpe me I haue but xii. pens. and pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked owte the ſame of a lytle purſſe, why haue you no more quoth they, no ſayth thys Cranke as God ſhall ſaue my ſoule at the daye of iudgement, we muſt ſee more quoth they and beegane to ſtrype hym, then he plucked out a nother purſſe wherein was xl. d. Touſhe ſayth thys Prynter I muſt ſee more, Sayth this Cranke I pray God I bee dampned both body and ſoule yf I haue anye more, no ſayth thys Prynter thou falſe knaue here is my boye that dyd watche thee all thys day and ſawe when ſuche men gaue the peeſes of ſyxe pens grotes and other money and yet thou haſt ſhewed vs none but ſmall money, when thys Cranke harde thys and the boye vowynge it to hys face he relented, and plucked out a nother purſſe wherein was eyght ſhyllynges and odde mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſo hade they in the hole that he hadde begged that day xiii. s. iii d. ob. then they ſtrypt hym ſtarcke naked and as manye as ſawe hym ſayde they neuer ſawe hanſommer man wyth a yellow flexen hede and fayre ſknned wythout any ſpotte or greffe then the good wyfe of the howſe fet her mans olde clocke and cawſed the ſame to bee caſte abowte hym beecawſe the ſyght ſhould not abaſhe her ſhamefaſt maydens nether lothe her ſquamyſhe ſyght.</p>
            <p>Thus he ſette hym downe at the Chemnes ende and called for a potte of Beere and dranke of a quart at a drafte, and called for a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother and ſo the thyrde, that one hadde byn ſufficient for any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man, the Drynke was ſo ſtronge I my ſelfe the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge taſted thereof but lette the reader iudge what and howe muche he woulde haue dronke and hee hadde byne owte of feare
<pb facs="tcp:12796:17"/> then when they had thus wronge water out of a flint, in ſpoyling him of his euil gotten goods his paſſing pence and fleting traſhe. The printer with this officer were in gealy gelowſy, and deuiſed to ſearch a barne for ſome roges and vprighte men, a quarter of a mile from the houſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtode alone in the fieldes, &amp; went out about their buſines leauing this cranke alone with his wife &amp; maydens, this crafty Cranke eſpyeng all gone, requeſted the good wife that he might goe out on the backſide to make water and to exonerate his paunch, ſhe had him drawe the lach of the dore and go out, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther thinking or miſtruſting he would haue gone away naked, but to conclude, when he was out he caſt away the cloke and as naked as euer he was borne he ranne away that he woulde neuer be hard of again til now the next morning betimes I went vnto Newing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton to vnderſtande what was done, becauſe I had worde or it was day that there my printer was, and at my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming thether I harde the hole circumſtance as I aboue haue written, &amp; I ſeing the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo fal out, toke order with the chiefe of the pariſh that this .xiii. s. and .iii. d. ob. might the nexte day be equally diſtributed by their good diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to the pouerty of the ſame pariſh, &amp; ſo it was done.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>A Dommerar.</head>
            <p>THeſe Dommerars are leud and moſt ſubtill people, the moſt part of theſe are Walch men, and wil neuer ſpeake, vnleſſe they haue extreame puniſhmente, but will gape, and with a maruelous force wil hold downe their toungs doubled, gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninge for your charity, and holding vp their handes full pitiouſly, ſo that with their deepe diſſimulation they get very much. There are of theſe many, and but one that I vnderſtand of hath loſte hys tounge in dede. Hauinge on a time occaſion to ride to Dartford to ſpeake with a prieſt there, who maketh al kinde of conſerues very well, and vſeth ſtillinge of waters. And repayringe to his houſe I founde a Dommerar at his dore, and the prieſt himſelfe peruſinge of his lycence, vnder the ſeales and handes of certayn worſhipfull men, which prieſt had thought the ſame to be good and effectuall. I taking the ſame writing, and reading it ouer &amp; noting the ſeals found one of the ſeals like vnto a ſeale that I had about me, which ſeale I bought beſides Charing croſſe, that I was out of doubte it was none of thoſe Gentlemens ſeales that had ſubcribed. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnderſtanding before of their peuiſh practiſes, made me to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue that al was forged and nought. I made the more haſt home,
<pb facs="tcp:12796:17"/> For well I wyſt that he woulde &amp; muſt of force paſſe through the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſh where I dwelt, for there was no other waye for hym. And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming homewarde, I found them in the towne accordinge to my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, where they were ſtaid: for there was a Pallyarde aſociat with the Dommerar and partaker of his gaynes, whyche Pallyarde I ſawe not at Dartforde. The ſtayers of them was a gentleman cal- <hi>Chayne,</hi> &amp; aſaruant of my Lord Kéepers, cald <hi>Woſteſtowe,</hi> which was the chiefe cauſer of the ſtayng of them, being a Surgien, &amp; cunninge in his ſcience, had ſéene the lyke practiſes, and as he ſayde hadde cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one to ſpeake afore that was dumme. It was my chaunce to com at the begynnyng of the matter. Syr (quoth this Surgen) I am bold here to vtter ſome part of my cunning, I truſt (quoth he) you ſhall ſée a myracle wrought anon. For I once (quoth he) made a dumme man to ſpeake. Quoth I you ar well met, and ſomwhat you haue preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, for I had thought to haue done no leſſe or they hadde paſſed this towne. For I well know their writing is fayned, and they depe diſſemblers. The Surgien made hym gape, &amp; we could ſée but halfe a toung. I required the Surgien to put hys fynger in his mouth, &amp; to pull out his toung, and ſo he did, notwithſtanding he helde ſtrongly a prety whyle, at the length he pluckt out the ſame, to the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of many that ſtoode by. Yet when we ſawe his tounge, he would neither ſpeake, nor yet could heare Quoth I to the Surgien, knit two of his ſyngers together, and thruſt a ſtycke betwene them, and rubbe the ſame vp and downe a lyttle while, and for my lyfe he ſpeaketh by and by. Sir quoth this Surgien I pray you let me prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe an other way. I was well contented to ſée the ſame. He had him into a houſe, and tyed a halter aboute the wreſtes of his handes and hoyſed him vp ouer a beame, and there did let him hang a good while. at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length for very payn, he required for Gods ſake to let him down. So he that was both deafe and du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me coulde in ſhort time both heare and ſpeake. Then I tooke that money I could finde in his purſe, and diſtributed the ſame to the poore people dwelling there, whiche was xv. pence halfe penny, beinge all that we could finde. That done, &amp; this merry myracle madly made, I ſent them with my ſeruaunt to the next Iuſticer, where they preached on the Pyllery for want of a Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and were well whypped, and none dyd bewayle them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A dronken Tinckar.</head>
            <p>THeſe dronken Tynckers called alſo Prygges, be beaſtly people, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:12796:18"/> theſe yong knaues be the wurſt. Theſe neuer go w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out their Dores, and yf their women haue anye thing about them, as apparell or lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen that is worth the ſelling, they laye the ſame to gage, or ſell it out right (for bene bowſe at their bowſing ken.) And full ſone wyll they bee wearye of them, and haue a newe. When they happen one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orke at anye good houſe, their Dores lynger a lofe, &amp; tarrye for them in ſome corner, and yf he taryeth longe from her, then ſhe knoweth he hathe worke, &amp; walketh neare, and ſytteth downe by him. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes money he looketh for meate and drinke for doing his dame plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. For yf ſhe haue three or foure holes in a pan, hee wyll make as many more for ſpedy gayn. And if he ſe any old ketel, chafer, or pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdiſh a broad in the yarde where he woorketh, hée quicklye ſnappeth the ſame vp, and into the booget it goethe rounde. Thus they lyue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> decrite. I was crediblye informed by ſuch as could well tell, that one of theſe tipling Tinckers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his dogge robbed by the highe waye .iiii. Pallyardes, and .ij. Roges .vj. perſons together, and tooke from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue .iiij. pound in ready money, &amp; hide him after in a thicke woode a daye or two, and ſo eſcaped vntaken. Thus with picking and ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, mingled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a litle worke for a coullor, they paſſe their tyme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Swadder or Pedler</head>
            <p>THeſe Swadders &amp; pedlers, be not all euyl, but of an indifferent behauiour. Theſe ſtande in great awe of the vpryght men, for they haue often both wares &amp; money of them. But for as much as they ſéeke gayne vnlawfully aganſt the lawes and ſtatutes of this noble realme, thei are well worthy to be regiſtred among y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nomber of vacabonds, &amp; vndoubtedly I haue hadde ſome of them brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me when I was in comiſſion of the peace as malefactors for bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering &amp; ſtealing. And nowe of late it is a great practes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpright man, when he hath gotten a botye to beſtowe the ſame vpon a packe full of wares, &amp; ſo goethe a time for his pleſure becauſe he would lyue with out ſuſpition.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Iarkeman, And a Patrico.</head>
            <p>FOras muche as theſe two names a Iarkeman and a Patrico be in the old briefe of vacabonds, and ſetforthe as two kyndes of euell doers, you ſhall vnderſtande that a Iarkmane hathe his name of a Iarke, which is a ſeale in their Languag, as one ſhould make wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and ſet ſeales for lycences and paſportes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:18"/>
            <p>And for trouth there is none that goeth about the countrey of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can eyther wryte ſo good and fayre a hand, either indite ſo learnedlye as I haue ſene and handeled a number of them: but haue the ſame made in good townes where they come, as what can not be had for money, as the prouerbe ſaythe <hi>(Omnia venalia Rome)</hi> and manye hath confeſſed the ſame to me. Now alſo there is a Patrico and not a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch, which in their language is a prieſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould make mariages tyll death dyd departe, but they haue none ſuche I am well aſſured, for I put you out of doubte that not one amongeſt a hundreth of them are maried, for they take lechery for no ſynne, but naturall fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp and good lyiknge loue, ſo that I wyll not blot my booke wyth theſe two that be not.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Demaunder for glymmar.</head>
            <p>THeſe Demaunderes for glymmar be for the moſt parte wemen, for glymmar in their language is fyre: theſe go with faynen ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences and counterfayted wrytings, hauing the hands and ſeales of ſuche gentlemen as dwelleth nere to the place where they fayne them ſelues to haue bene burnt and their goods conſumed with fyre. They wyll moſt lamentably demaunde your charity, &amp; wyll quickly ſhed ſalte teares, they be ſo tender harted. They will neuer begge in that Shiere where their loſſes (as they ſaye) was. Some of theſe goe with ſlates at their backes, which is a ſhéete to lye in a nightes. The vpright men be very familiar wyth theſe kynde of women, and one of them helpes an other. ¶ A Demaunder for glymmar came vnto a good towne in Kent to aſke the cheritie of the people, hauing a fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned lycens aboute her that declared her miſfortune by fyre, donne in Somerſet ſhyre, walking with a wallet on her ſhoulders wherin ſhe put the deuotion of ſuch as had no money to geue, here that is to ſay, Malte, woll, baken, bread, and cheeſe, and alwayes as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame was full, ſo was it redy money to her when ſhe emptyed the ſame, where ſo euer ſhe traueled this harlot was as they terme it ſnowte fayre and had an Vpright man or two alwayes attending on her watch (which is on her parſon) and yet ſo circomſpecte that they woulde neuer bee ſene in her company in any good towne vnleſſe it were in ſmale vyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages where typling houſes weare, eyther traueling to gether by the hygh ways, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troth is by report ſhe would wekely be worth vi. or ſeuen ſhyllinges, with her begging and bycherye. This glimmeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Morte repayring to an Ine in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde towne, where dwelt a wydow
<pb facs="tcp:12796:19"/> of fyfty wynter olde of good welthe but ſhe had an vnthryftye ſonne, whom ſhe vſed as a chamberlaine to attend geſtes when they repard to her houſe, this amerous man beholding with ardant eyes, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge this glymmeringe glauncer was preſently peteouſly perſed to the harte, and lewdly longed to be clothed vnder her lyuerye and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing a fewe fonde wordes, wyth her, vnderſtode ſtrayte, that ſhe woulde be eaſlye perſwaded to lykinge lechery, and as a man maſed muſed howe to attayne to his purpoſe, but he hadde no money. Yet conſideringe with hym ſelfe that wares woulde bee welcome where money wanted, he went with a wannion to his mothers chamber &amp; there ſekinge about for od endes, at length found a lytle whyſtell of ſyluer that his mother dyd vſe cuſtomably to weare on, and had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gote the ſame for haſte that morning, and offeres the ſame cloſely to this manerly marian that yf ſhe would mete him on the backeſyde of the towne and curteouſly kys him without conſtraynt ſhe ſhould bee myſtres thereof and it weare much better, well ſaythe ſhe you are a wanton, and beholding the wyſtell was farthar in loue therewyth, then rauyſht wyth his perſon and agred to mete him preſently and to accomplyſhe his fonde fancy, to be ſhort and not tedyous a quorter of a myle from the towne he merely toke meaſure of her vnder a bawdy buſhe (ſo ſhe gaue him that ſhe had not) and he receiued that he could not) and taking leue of ech other with a curteous kyſſe, ſhe pleſantly paſſed forth one her iornaye &amp; this vntoward lycorous chamberlayne repayred home warde. But or theſe two tortylles toke there leue the good wyfe had myſſed her whyſtell, and ſent one of her maydens in to her chamber for the ſame, and being long ſawght for none coulde be found, her myſtres hering that dylygent ſearch was made for the fame, and that it was taken awaye, began to ſuſpecte her vnbleſſed babe, and demaunded of her maydens whether none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſawe her ſonne in her chamber that morning, and one of them anſwered that ſhe ſawe him not there but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from thence, then had ſhe ynough for well ſhe wyſte that he had the ſame, and ſent for him but he could not be found. Then ſhe cauſed her hoſteler in whome ſhe had better affyaunce in for his trouth and yet not one amongſt twenty of them but haue well left there honeſty (As I here a great ſorte ſaye) to com vnto here which attended to knowe her pleafure, go ſeke out ſaythe ſhe my vntowarde ſonne and byd him come ſpeake with me, I ſawe him go out ſayth he halfe an our ſithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> backſid I had thought you had ſent hym of your arrante, I ſent hym not ꝙ ſhe go loke him out.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12796:19"/> This hollowe hoſteler toke his ſtaffe in his necke and trodged out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace that waye he ſawe him before go and had ſome vnderſtandinge by one of the maydens that his myſtres hadde her wyſtell ſtolen and ſuſpected her ſonne, and he had not gone far but that hee eſpyed hym comming homeward alone, and meting him axed where he had byn. Where haue I bene ꝙ he and began to ſmyle, now by the mas thou haſt bene at ſome baudy banquet, thou haſt euen tolde trouth ꝙ thys chamberlayne ſewrely ꝙ this hoſtler thou haedeſt the ſame woman that begged at our houſe to daye for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harmes ſhe had by fyre, where is ſhe ꝙ he ſhe is almoſt a myle by this tyme ꝙ this chamberlayne, where is my myſtres whyſtell quoth this hoſteler for I am well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that thou haddeſt it and I feare me thou haſt geuen it to that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot. Why is it myſſed quoth this chamberlayne, yea ꝙ this hoſteler and ſhewed him all the hole circomſtaunce what was both ſayde and thought on hym for the thinge. Well I wyll tell the ꝙ this Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlayne I wylbe playne with the I had it in dede and haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame to this woman, and I praye the make the beſt of it and helpe nowe to excuſe the matter, and yet ſurelye and thou wouldſt take ſo much payne for me as to ouer take her for ſhe goeth but ſoftly and is not yet fare of and take the ſame from her and I am euer thyne aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red freende. Why then go with me quoth this hoſtler, nay in faythe quoth this Chamberlayne what is frear then gift, and I hadde prety paſtime for the ſame, hadeſt thou ſo quoth this hoſteler nowe by the maſſe and I wyll haue ſome to or I wyll lye in the duſte or I come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Paſſing with haſt to ouertake this paramoure within a myle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where he departed he ouertoke her hauing an vpright ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in her company a ſtronge and a ſturdye vacabond ſome what amaſed was this hoſteler to ſe one familiarly in her company for he had well hopped to haue had ſome delycate dalyance as his fellowe hadde but ſeinge the matter ſo fall out and being of good corrage and thinking to him ſelfe that one true man was better then two falſe knaues and being on the hygh way thought vpon helpe yf nede had bene by ſuch as had paſſed to and fro. Demaunded ferſely the whiſtell that ſhe had euyn nowe of his fellowe, why huſband quoth ſhe can you ſuffer this wretche to ſlaunder your wyfe, a vaunt verlet ꝙ this vpright man and letes dryue with all his force at this hoſteler and after halfe a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen blowes he ſtrycks his ſtaffe out of his hand, and as this hoſteler ſtepte backe to haue taken vp his ſtaffe agayne, this glymmeringe Morte flinges a great ſtone at him and ſtrake him on the heade that
<pb facs="tcp:12796:20"/> downe he fals wyth the bloud about his eares and whyle he laye this amaſed the vpright man ſnatches awaye hys purſe, wherein he had money of his myſtreſſes as well as of his owne, and there let him lie and went awaye with ſpede that they were neuer hard of more. When this drye beaten hoſteler was com to him ſelfe he fayntly wandereth home, and crepethe into his couche and reſtes hys ydle head, hys myſtrys harde that he was come in, and layde him downe on his bead, repayred ſtraight vnto him and aſke him what he ayled and what the cauſe was of his ſo ſodden lying one his bed, what is the cauſe quoth this hoſteler your whyſtell your whyſtell ſpeaking the ſame pytiouſly iii. or iiii. tymes, why fole quoth his myſtres take no care for that, for I do not greatly waye it, it was worth but iii. s. iiii. d. I would it had bene burnt for iiii. yeares agon, I praye the why ſo quoth hys myſtres I thinke thou art mad, nay not yet qd. this hoſteler but I haue byn madly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd, why what is the matter quoth his myſtres and was more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to knowe the cauſe, and you wyll for geue my fellowe and me I wyll ſhewe you, or els I wyll neuer doe it, ſhee made hym preſently faythfull promiſe that ſhe would, then ſayth he ſend for your ſonne home agayne which is aſhamed to loke you in the face I agre there to ſayth ſhe, well then qd. thys hoſteler youre ſonne hath geuen the ſame Mort that begged here for the burning of her houſe a whyſtell and you haue geuen her v. s. in money, &amp; I haue geuen her x, s, of my owne, why how ſo quoth ſhe, then he ſadlye ſhewed her of hys myſhap with al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circomſtaunce that you haue hard before, and howe hys purſe was taken awaye &amp; xv ſhyllings in the ſame, wherof v. s. was her money and x. s. his owne money is thys true quoth hys myſtres, I by my trouth qd. this hoſteler, and nothing greues me ſo much, neyther my beatyng neyther the loſſe of my money as doth my euel and wretched lucke, why what is the matter qd. his myſtres, your ſonne ſaythe thys hoſteler had ſome chere and paſtyme for that whyſtell for he laye with her, and I haue bene well beaten, and haue had my purſſe taken from me and you knowe your ſonne is merry and pleaſant and can kepe no great councell and then ſhall I be mocked and laughed to ſkorne in all places when they ſhall here how I haue bene ſerued, Nowe out vpon you knaues both quoth his myſtres, and laughes oute the matter, for ſhe well ſawe it would not otherwyſe preuayle.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A bawdy baſket.</head>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:12796:20"/>
            <p>THeſe bawdy baſkets be alſo wemen, and go with baſkets &amp; Capcaſes on their armes, wherin they haue laces, pynnes, nedles, white ynkell, and round ſylke gyrdls of al coulours. Theſe wyll bye conueyſkins, &amp; ſtele lynnen clothes of on hedges. And for their tryfles they wyl procure of mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruauntes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their myſtres or dame is out of the way, eyther ſome good pece of beefe, baken, or cheeſe, that ſhalbe worth xii. d. for ii. d. of their to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes. And as they walke by the way, they often gayne ſome money wyth their inſtrument, by ſuche as they ſodaynely mete withall. The vpright men haue good acquayntaunce with theſe, and wyl helpe and relieue them when they wante. Thus they trade their lyues in leud lothſome lechery. Amongeſt them all is but one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt woman, and ſhe is of good yeares, her name is Ione Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I haue had good proofe of her. as I haue learned by the true report of dyuers, Thre came to my gate the laſte ſommer. Anno Domni. 1566. a very miſerable man and much deformed as burnt in the face blere eyde and lame of one of his legges that he wente with a crouche, I axed him where he was borne &amp; where he dwelt laſt and ſhewed him that thether he muſt repaire and be releued &amp; not to range about the countrey, and ſeing ſome cauſe of cheryte I cauſed him to haue meate and drinke and when he had dronke I demaunded of him whether he was neuer ſpoyled of the vpryght man or Roge, yes that I haue qd be and not this vii. yeres for ſo long I haue gon abroad, I had not ſo much taken from me and ſo euyll handelyd as I was within theſe iiii. dayes, why how ſo ꝙ I in good fayth ſir ꝙ he I chaunced to mete with on of thefe bawdy baſkets which had an vpright man in her company, &amp; as I would haue paſſed quietly by her, man ſaythe ſhe vnto her make, doe you not ſe this ylfauored windſhaken knaue, yes qd. the vpright man what ſay you to him, thys knaue fayth ſhe oweth me ii. s, for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res that he had of me halfe a yere a go I thynke it well ſayth this vpright man ſyrra ſayth he paye your detes, ſaith thys poore man I owe her none nether dyd I euer bargane w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her for any thinge and as thys aduyſed I neuer ſawe her before in all my lyfe, mercy god quoth ſhe what a lying knaue is this, and he wyll not paye you houſband beat hym ſurely, and the vpryght man gaue me iii. or iiii. blowes on my backe and ſhoulders and woulde haue beate me worſſe and I had not geuen hym all the money in my purſe &amp; in good fayth for very feare I was fayne to geue hym xiiii. pence which was all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> money that I had, why ſayth this bawdy baſket
<pb facs="tcp:12796:21"/> haſte thou no more, then thou oweſt me x. d. ſtyll, and be well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that I wylbe payde the next tyme I meete with the. And ſo they let me paſſe by them. I praye god ſaue &amp; bleſſe me and all other in my caſe from ſuch wycked perſons quoth this poore man, why whether went they then quoth I in to eaſt Kent for I méete w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them on thyſſid of Rocheſter. I haue dyuers times bene attempted but I neuer loſte much before, I thanke god there came ſtyll company by afore this vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>happy time. Well quoth I thanke God of all, and repair home into thy natyue countrey.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Antem morte.</head>
            <p>THeſe Antem Mortes be maried wemen, as there be but a fewe. For Antem in their Language is a Churche, ſo ſhe is a wyfe maried at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churche, and they be as chaſte as a Cowe. I haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goeth to Bull euery moone, with what Bull ſhe careth not. Theſe walke moſt times from their houſbands companye a moneth &amp; more to gether, being aſociate with another as honeſt as her ſelfe. Theſe wyll pylfar clothes of hedges, ſome of them go with children of .x. or xii. yeares of age, yf tyme and place ſerue for their purpoſe they wyll ſend them into ſome houſe at the window to ſteale and robbe, which they call in their language, Milling of the ken, &amp; wyll go w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wallets on their ſhoulders, and ſlates at their backs: there is one of theſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Mortes ſhe is now a widow, of fyfty yeres old, her name is Alice Milſon, ſhe goeth about with a couple of great boyes, the yongeſt of them is faſt vpon xx. yeres of age and theſe two do lye with her euery night, and ſhe lyeth in the middes, ſhe ſayth that they be her childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that beteled be the babes borne of ſuch abhonable bellye.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A walking Morte.</head>
            <p>THeſe walkinge Mortes be not maryed, theſe for their vnhappye yeres doth goe as a Antem Morte, and wyll ſaye their huſbandes died eyther at Newhauen Ireland, or in ſome ſeruice of the Prince. Theſe make laces vpon ſtaues &amp; purſes that they cary in their hands, and whyte vallance for beddes. Manye of theſe hathe had, and haue chyldren: when theſe get ought, either with begging bychery or bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, as money or apparell, they are quickly ſhaken out of all by the vpright men, that they are in a maruelous feare to cary any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute them that is of ſome valure. Wherefore this pollicy they vſe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12796:21"/> they leaue their money now with on and then with another truſtye houſeholders either with the good man or good wyfe, ſome tyme in won ſhiere, and then in another as they trauell, this haue I known y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iiij. or v. ſhillings yea .x. ſhillinges lefte in a place and the ſame wyll they come for againe within won quarter of a yeare or ſome time not inhalfe a yeare, and all this is to lytle purpoſe, for all their peuyſhe pollicye, for when they bye them lynnen or garments, it is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from them and worſſe geuen them, or none at all. ¶ The laſt Sommer Anno Domni. 1566. beinge in familiare talke with a walking Morte, that came to my gate I learned by her what I could and I thought I had gathered as much for my purpoſe as I deſired. I began to rebuke her for her leud lyfe and beaſtly behauor, declaring to here what puniſhment was prepared and heaped vp for her in the world to com, for her fylthy lyuing and wretched conuerſation. God helpe ꝙ ſhe howe ſhould I lyue, none wyll take me into ſeruis, but I laboure in harueſt time honeſtly. I thinke but a whyle with honeſtie quoth I Shall I tell you ꝙ ſhe, the beſte of vs al maye be amended, but yet I thanke God, I ded on good dede within this twelue mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ths wherein ꝙ I, ſayth ſhe I woulde not haue it ſpoken of agayne. Yf it be méete and neceſſary ꝙ I it ſhal lye vnder my fete, what meane you by that quoth ſhe, I meane ꝙ I to hide the ſame &amp; neuer to diſcouer it to any. Well quoth ſhe and began to lawgh as much as ſhe coulde, and ſweare by the maſſe that if I diſcloſed the ſame to any ſhe would neuer more tell me any thing. The laſt ſommer ꝙ ſhe I was greate with chylde and I traueled into eaſt kent by the ſea coſte, for I luſted meruelouſly after oyſters and muſſels and gathered many, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where I found them, I opened them and eat them ſtyll, at the laſt in ſeking more I reached after one and ſtept into a hole and felin into the waſt and their did ſtycke, and I had bene drowned if the tide had come, and eſpyinge a man a good waye of, I cried as much as I could for helpe, I was alone he hard me and repaired as faſt to me as he might and finding me their faſt ſtycking, I required for gods ſake his helpe, and whether it was with ſtryuing and forcing my ſelfe out or for Ioye I had of his comminge to me. I had a great couller in my face and loked red and well tollered. And to be playne with you hée lyked me ſo wel (as he ſayd) that I ſhould there lye ſtyll, and I would not graunt him, that he myghtly with me. And by my trouth I wiſt not what to anſweare I was in ſuch a perplexite, for I knewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man well, he had a very honeſt woman to his wyfe and was of ſom welth
<pb facs="tcp:12796:22"/> and on the other ſyde if I weare not helpe oute I ſhoulde there haue peryſhed, and I graunted hym that I would obeye to hys wyll, then he plucked me out. And becauſe there was no conuenient place nere hande, I required hym that I might go waſhe my ſelfe and make me ſome what clenly, and I would come to his houſe and lodge al night in his barne, whether he myghte repaire to me and accomplyſhe hys deſire, but let it not be quoth ſhée before nine of the clocke at nighte for then there wylbe ſmall ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yrring. And I may repayre to the town ꝙ ſhe to warme and drye my ſelfe, for this was about two of the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cke in the after noune do ſo quoth hée for I muſt be buſye to loke oute my cattell here by before I can come home. So I went awaye from hym and glad was I, and why ſo quoth I, becauſe quoth ſhe his wyfe my good dame is my very fréend, and I am much beholdinge to her. And ſhe hath donne are ſo much good or this that I we are loth nowe to harme her any way<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to by quoth I what and it hadde bene anye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther man and not your good dames huſbande. The matter had bene the leſſe quoth ſhée. Tell me I praye the quoth I who was the father of thye chylde ſhe ſtodyed a whyle, and ſayde that it hadde a father but what was hée quoth I. Nowe by my trouthe I knowe not quoth ſhée, you brynge me ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of my matter ſoo you do, well ſaye on quoth I then I departed ſtrayght to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne and came to my dames houſe. And ſhewed here of my myſfortune, alſo of here huſebandes vſage in all poyntes and that I ſhowed here the ſame for good wyll and byde her take better hede to her houſebande, and to her ſelfe, ſo ſhe gaue me grate thankes and made me good cheere, and byd me in any caſe that I ſhouldde be redye at the barne at that tyme and oure we hadde apoynted, for I knowe well quoth thys good wyfe, my huſband wyll not breake wyth the. And one thinge I warrant the that thou geue me a watche worde a loude when he goeth aboute to haue his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the and that ſhould be fie for ſhame fye, and I wyll be hard by you wythe helpe. But I charge the kéepe thys ſecrete vntyll all bée fyneſed, and holde ſaythe thys good wyfe here is one of my peticotes I geue the. I thanke you good dame qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h I, and I warraunte you I wyll bée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue and truſtye vnto you. So my dau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e me ſettynge by a good fyre wyth meate and drynke, and wyth the oyſters I brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte with me, I hadde greate the ere ſhée wente ſtrayght and repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto her goſſypes dwellyng there by, and as I dyd after vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſhe made her mone to thee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. what a naughti lend lecherous huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhe had, and how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe could not haue his companye for harlots,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12796:22"/> and that ſhe was in feare to take ſome fylthy dyſeaſe of hym, he was ſo commen a man hauing lytle reſpecte whome he hadde to doe with all, and quoth ſhe nowe here is one at my houſe a poore woman that goeth aboute the countrey that he woulde haue hadde to doo withall wherefore good neyghboures and louinge goſſypes as you loue me and as you would haue helpe at my hand another tyme, deuyſe ſome remedy to make my huſband a good man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may lyue in ſum ſuerty wyth out diſeaſe, and that hée maye ſaue his ſoull that God ſo derelye bought. After ſhée hadde tolde her tale they caſte their perſinge eyes all vpon her, but won ſtoute dame amongſt the reſt had theſe words as your pacient bearinge of troubles, youre honeſt behauor amonge vs, your neyghbours your tender and pytiful hart to the poore of the paryſh, doth moue vs to lament your caſe, ſo the vnſatiable carnalite of your faytheleſſe huſbande doth inſtigate and ſtyre vs to deuyſe and inuent ſome ſpéedy redreſſe for your eaſe and the amendement of his lyfe. Wherefore thys is my councell and you wyll bée aduertyſed by me, for I ſaye to you all, vnles it be thys good wyfe, who is chéefely touched in this matter I haue the nexte cauſe, for hée was in hande wyth me not longe a goe, and companye had not bene preſent which was by a meruelous chaunce, he hadde I thinke forced me. For often hée hathe bene temperinge with me, and yet haue I ſharpely ſayde hym naye, therefore let vs aſſemble ſecretly into the place where hée hathe apoynted to méete this gyllot that is at youre houſe and lyrke preuely in ſeme corner tyll hée begyn to goe aboute his buſines. And then me thought I harde you ſaye euen now that you had a watche worde, at whyche worde wée wyll all ſtep forthe being fyue of vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes you for you ſhalbe none becauſe it is youre huſbande, but gette you to bed at your accuſtomed our. And we wyll cary eche of vs a good byrchen rodd in our lappes, and we wyll all be muffeled for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and ſe that you go home and acquaynt that walking Morte with the matter for we muſt haue her helpe to hold, for alwaies foure muſt hold &amp; two lay one. Alas ſayth this good wyfe, he is to ſtronge for you al, I would be loth for my ſake you ſhould receaue harme at his hand feare you not ꝙ theſe ſtout wemen let her not geue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> watche worde vntyll his hoſen be aboute his leggs. And I trowe we all wylbe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him to bryng before he ſhall haue leyſure to plucke them vp agayne they al w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> on voyce agred to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the way ſhe had deuiſed was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt, ſo this good wife repaired home but before ſhe departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her goſſyps ſhe ſhewed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at what oure they ſhould preuely come in on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> backſyd &amp; where to tary their good our, ſo by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time ſhe cam in it was all moſte night,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:23"/>
            <p>and found the walking Morte ſtyll ſetting by the fyre, and declared to her all this new deuyſe aboue ſayd, which promiſed faythfully to full<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyll to her ſmall powre as much as they had deuyſed, with in a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an owre after in commeth the good man, who ſaid that he was about his cattell, why what haue we here wyfe ſetting by the fyre, &amp; yf ſhe haue eate and dronke ſend her into the barne to her lodging for this night, for ſhe troubeleth the houſe, euen as you wyll houſbande ſayth his wyfe you knowe ſhe commeth once in two yeres into theſe quarters. Awaye ſaythe this good wyfe to your lodginge, yes good dame ſayth ſhe as faſt as I can, thus by loking won on the other eche knewe others mind and ſo departed, to her comely couche, the good man of the houſe ſhrodge hym for Ioye thinking to hym ſelfe I wyll make ſome paſtyme with you anone. And calling to his wyfe for his ſopper ſet him downe and was very pleſant and dranke to his wyfe &amp; fell to his mamerings and mouched a pace nothing vnderſtanding of the banckquet that was a preparing for him after ſopper, &amp; according to the prouerbe. (Swere meate wyll haue ſowre ſawce) thus when he was well refreſhed, his ſprietes being reuyued entred into familiare talke with his wyfe, of manye matters hawe well he had ſpent that daye to both there proffytes, ſaying ſome of his cattell that were lyke to haue bene drowned in the deches dryuing others of his neyghbors cattell out that were in his paſtures, &amp; mending his fences that were broken downe. Thus profitably he had conſumed the daye, nothing talking of his helping out of the walking Morte out of the myre, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his requeſt nor yet of her promiſſe. Thus feding her w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> frendly ſantycyes conſumed two oures and more. Then fayninge howe hee would ſe in what caſe his horſe were in and howe they were dreſſed. Repaired couetly in to the barne, where as his freendely foes lyrked preuely vnles it were this mannerly Morte, that comly couched on a bottell of ſtrawe, what are you come ꝙ ſhe by the maſſe I would not for a hundreth pound that my dame ſhould knowe that you were here eyther any els of your houſe. No I warrant the ſayth this good man they be all ſafe and faſt ynough at their worke, and I wylbe at mine anone. And laye downe by her, and ſtrayght would haue had to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her, nay lye ſayth ſhe I lyke not this order if ye lye with me you ſhall ſurely vntrus you &amp; put down your hoſen for that way is moſt eaſieſt and beſt, ſayeſt thou ſo quoth he now by my trouth agred. And when he had vntruſſed him ſelfe and put downe he began to aſſalt the vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able fort, why quoth ſhe that was with out ſhame ſauinge for here
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12796:23"/> promes. And are you not aſhamed, neuer a whyt ſayth he lye downe quickely, now fye for ſhame, fye ſaythe ſhe a loude whyche was the watche word. At the which word, theſe fyne furious ſturdy muffeled goſſypes flynges oute, and takes ſure holde of this betrayed parſon, ſone plucking his hoſen downe lower, and bynding the ſame faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his féete, then bynding his handes, and knittinge a hande char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher about hys eyes, that he ſhould not ſée, and when they had made hym ſure and faſt. Then they layd hym one vntyll they weare wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, be good ſayth this Morte vnto my maiſter for the paſcion of god and layd on as faſt as the reſt, and ſtyll ſeaſed not to crye vpon them to bee mercyfull vnto hym, and yet layde on a pace, and when they had well beaten hym that the bloud braſte plentifullye oute in moſte places they let hym lye ſtyll bounde. With this exortation, that he ſhould from that tyme forth know his wyfe from other mens and that this puniſhment was but a flebyting in reſpecte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych ſhould followe, yf he amended not his manners. Thus leuyng hym bluſtering blowing and fominge for payne and malyncolye that hee nether myght or coulde be reuenged of them, they vanyſhed awaye and hadde thys Morte wyth them, and ſafely conuayde her out of the town, ſone after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth into the barne one of the good mans boyes to ſet ſome haye for his horſe. And fyndinge his maiſter lyinge faſte bounde and greuouſlye beaten with rades, was ſodenly abaſhed and would haue runne out ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yne to haue called for helpe, but his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter bed hym come vnto hym and vnbynd hym. and make no wordes quoth he of this. I wylbe reuenged well ynoughe, yet not wythſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge after better aduyſe, the mattor beinge vnhoneſt; he thought it meter to let the ſame pas, and not as the prouerbe ſaythe (to awake the ſleping dogge.) And by my trouth quoth this walkinge Morte, I come nowe from that place and was neuer there ſythence this parte was playde, which is ſome what more then a yeare. And I here a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good reporte of hym, now that he loueth hys wyfe well and vſeth hym ſelfe verye honeſtlye and was not this a good acte, nowe howe ſaye you. It was pretelye handeled quoth I and is here all yea quoth ſhe here is the ende.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Doxe.</head>
            <p>THeſe Doxes be broken and ſpoyled of their maydenhead, by the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right men, and then they haue their name of Doxes, and not afore And afterward ſhe is commen and indifferent for any that wyll vſe
<pb facs="tcp:12796:24"/> her as <hi>homo</hi> is a commen name to all men. Such as be fayre and ſome what handſome, kepe company with the walkinge Mortes, and are redye alwayes for the vpright men, and are chiefely mayntayned by them, for others ſhalbe ſpoyled for their ſakes, the other in ferior ſort wyll reſorte to noble mens places, and gentlemens houſes ſtanding at the gate, eyther lurkinge on the backeſyde about backehouſes ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in hedge rowes or ſome other thycket, expectinge their praye, whiche is for the vncomely company of ſome curteous ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of whom they be refreſhed with meate and ſome monye, where eſchaunge is made ware for ware: this bread and meate they vſe to carry in their greate hoſen, ſo that theſe beaſtlye bryberinge bréeches ſerue manye tymes for bawdye purpoſes. I chaunced not longe ſithens familiarly to commen wyth a Doxe that came to my gate, and ſurelye a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant harlot, and not ſo pleaſant as wytty, and not ſo wytty as voyd of all grace and goodnes. I founde by here talke that ſhée hadde paſſed her tyme lewdlye eyghttene yeares in walkinge aboute. I thoughte this a neceſſary inſtrument to attayne ſome knoweledge by, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I woulde grope her mynde I made her bothe to eate and drynke well, that done I made her faythefull promiſe to geue her ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney yf ſhe would open and dyſcouer to me ſuch queſtions as I would demaunde of her, and neuer to bee wraye her nether to diſcloſe her name. And you ſhoulde ſayth ſhe I were vndon: feare not that quoth I, but I praye the quoth I, ſay nothing but trouth. I wyll not ſaith ſhée, then fyrſte tell me quoth I, how many vpright men and Roges doſt thou knowe or haſt thou knowne and byn conuerſant with and what their names be: ſhe pauſed a whyle and ſayd: why do you aſke me, or wherefore? For nothinge els as I ſayde; but that I woulde knowe them when they came to my gate. Nowe by my trouth (quoth ſhe (then are yea neuer the neare, for all myne acquayntance for the moſte parte are deade. Dead quoth I, howe dyed they, for wante of cheriſhinge, or of paynefull diſeaſes. Then ſhe ſighed; and ſayde they were hanged. What all quoth I, and ſo manye walke abroade, as I dayely ſée? By my trouth quoth ſhe, I knowe not paſte ſix or ſeuen by their names, and named the ſame to me. When were they ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged quoth I? Some ſeuen yeares agone, ſome thrée yeares, and ſome w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this fortnight, and declared the place where they weare executed, whiche I knew well to bée true, by the reporte of others. Why (quoth I) dyd not this ſorrowfull and feareful ſight much gréeue thée, and for thy tyme longe and euyll ſpent. I was ſory quoth ſhée, by the Maſſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12796:24"/> for ſome of them were good louing men. For I lackt not when they had it, and they wanted not when I had it, and diuers of them I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dyd for ſake, vntyll the Gallowes departed vs. O mercyfull God (quoth I and began to bleſſe me. Why bleſſe ye quoth ſhe? Alas good gentleman euery one muſte haue a lyuinge. Other matters I talked of, but this nowe maye ſuffice to ſhewe the Reader as it weare in a glaſſe, the bolde beaſtly lyfe of theſe Dores. For ſuche as hathe gone anye tyme abroade, wyll neuer forſake their trade, to dye therefore, I haue hadde good profe thereof. There is one a notorious harlot of this affinitye called Beſſe Bottomelye, ſhe hath but one hande, and ſhe hath murthered two children at the leaſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Dell.</head>
            <p>A Dell is a yonge wencheable for generation, and not yet kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen or broken by the vpright man. Theſe go abroad yong, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the death of their parentes, and no bodye to looke vnto them, or els by ſome ſharpe myſtres that they ſerue do runne awaye oute of ſeruice, eyther ſhée is naturallye borne one, and then ſhée is a wylde Dell, theſe are broken verye younge, when they haue béene lyen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all by the vpright man, then they be Doxes, &amp; no Dels. Theſe wyld Dels being traded vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their monſtrous motheres, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſyty be as euil or wurſſe then their parents, for neither we gather grapes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grene bryars, neither fygs from Thiſtels. But ſuch buds, ſuch bloſoms, ſuch euyll ſede ſowen, well worſſe beinge growen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Kynchin Morte.</head>
            <p>A Kynchyn Morte is a lytle Gyrle, the Mortes their mothers car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries them at their backes in their ſtates, whiche is their ſhetes, and bryngs them vp ſafely, tyll they grow to be rype, and ſoone rype, ſoone rotten.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="type">
            <head>¶ A Kynchen Co.</head>
            <p>A Kynchen Co is a young boye, traden vp to ſuche peuiſhe purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as you haue hard of other young ympes before, that when he groweth two yeres, he is better to hang then to drawe forth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>¶ Their vſage in the night.</head>
            <p>NOw I thinke it not vnneceſſary to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Reader vndrſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n how &amp; in what maner they lodg a nights in barnes or backe-houſes, &amp; of their vſage ther, for aſmuch as I haue acquai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their order &amp; practiſes a day times. The arche &amp; chief walkers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath walked a long time, whoſe experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is great becauſe of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g practiſe, I meane all Morts &amp; Dores for their
<pb facs="tcp:12796:25"/> handſomnes and diligence for making of their couches. The men ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer trouble them ſelues with the thing, but takes the ſame to be the dutye of the wyfe. And ſhe ſhuffels vp a quantity of ſtrawe or haye in to ſome prety corner of the barne where ſhe maye conueniently lye, &amp; well ſhaketh the ſame, making the head ſome what hie, and driues y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vpon the ſydes and feete lyke a bed, then ſhe layeth her wallet, or ſome other litle packe of raggs or ſcrip vnder her head in the ſtraw to beare vp the ſame, and layeth her petycote or cloke vpon and ouer the ſtrawe ſo made lyke a bedde, &amp; that ſerueth for the blancket. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe layeth her ſtate which is her ſhete vpon that, &amp; ſhe haue no ſhete, as fewe of them go without, then ſhe ſpreddeth ſome large clouts or rags ouer the ſame, and maketh her ready, and layeth her drouſelye downe. Many wyll plucke of their ſmockes, and laye the ſame vpon them in ſtede of their vpper ſhéete, and all her other pelte and traſhe vpon her alſo, and many lyeth in their ſmockes. And if the reſt of her clothes in cold weather be not ſufficient to kepe her warme, then ſhe takethe ſtrawe or haye to performe the matter. The other ſorte that haue not ſlates, but toumble downe and couche a hogſhead in their clothes, and theſe be ſtyll louſy and ſhall neuer be with out vermin, vnles, they put of their clothes, and lye as is aboue ſayde. If the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man come in where they lye, he hath hys choyſe, and crepeth in cloſe by his Dore, the Roge hath his leauings. If the Mortes or Dox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es lye or be lodged in ſome Farmers barne, and the dore be etherloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked or made faſt to them, then wyl not the vpright man preſſe to com in. Vnles it be in barnes and oute houſes, ſtandinge alone, or ſome diſtance from houſes which be commonly knowne to them. As ſaint Quintens, thrée Cranes of the Vyntre, Saynt Tybbes, and Knapſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, Theſe foure be with in on myle compaſſe neare vnto London. Then haue you iiii. more in Middleſex, drawe the pudding out of the fyre, in Harrow on the hyll pariſh. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Croſe keyes in Cranford pariſh, Saynt Iulyans in Thiſtellworth pariſh, the houſe of pity, in North hall pariſh. Theſe are their chiefe houſes neare about London, wher commonly they reſorte vnto for Lodging, and maye repaire thether freelye at all times. Sometyme ſhall come in ſome Roge, ſome pye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king knaue, anymble Prygge, he walketh in ſoftly a nightes, when they be at their reſt and plucketh of as many garmentes as be ought worth that he maye come by, and worth money, and maye eaſely ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the ſame, and runneth awaye with the ſame with great felicitye, and maketh porte ſale at ſome conuenient place of theirs, that ſome
<pb facs="tcp:12796:25"/> ſoone ready in the morning, for want of their Caſters and Togema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Where in ſtéede of bleſſing is curſſing, in place of prainge peſtilente prayting with odious othes &amp; terrible threatninges. The vpright me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue geuen all theſe nycke names to the places aboue ſayd. Yt haue we twoo notable places in Kent, not fare from London, the one is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Detforde and Rothered, called the Kinges barne, ſtandyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that they haunt commonly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other is Ketbrok, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding by black heath halfe a mile fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any houſe. There wyll they boldlye drawe the latch of the doore, and go in when the good man with his famyly be at ſupper &amp; ſyt downe without leaue and eate and drinke with them, &amp; etherly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hal by the fire al night, or in the barne if ther be no rome in the houſe for them. If the doore be eyther bolted or lockt, if it be not opened vnto them when they wyll, they wyll breake the ſame opene to his farther coſt. And in this barne ſometyme do lye .xl. vpright men wyth their Doxes together at one time. And this muſt the poore Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſuffer, or els they threaten him to burne him, &amp; all that he hath.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="lists_of_individuals">
            <head>¶ The names of the Vpright men Roges, &amp; Palliardes.</head>
            <p>HEre followeth the vnrulye rablement of raſcals, and the moſte notorious and wyckedſt walkers that are lyuinge nowe at this preſent with then true names as they he called and knowne by. And although I ſet and place her but iii. orders, yet good Reader vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that all the others aboue named are deriued and come oute from the vpright men and Roges. Concerninge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of Morets and Dotes, it is ſuperfluous to write of them, I could well haue don it but the number of them is great, and would aſke a good volume.</p>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Vpright men.</head>
               <item>Richard Brymmyſh</item>
               <item>Iohn Myllar.</item>
               <item>Wel arayd Richard.</item>
               <item>Iohn Walchman.</item>
               <item>Thomas Bulloke.</item>
               <item>Iohn Iones.</item>
               <item>Ihon Teddar.</item>
               <item>Richard Iuſtyce.</item>
               <item>Lennard Iuſt.</item>
               <item>Robart Grauenar.</item>
               <item>Wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chamborne</item>
               <item>Bryan Medcalfe.</item>
               <item>Robart Gerſe.</item>
               <item>Gryffen.</item>
               <item>Core the Cuckolde.</item>
               <item>Robart Kynge.</item>
               <item>Nycholas Wylſon.</item>
               <item>Burfet.</item>
               <item>Iames Barnard.</item>
               <item>Stephen Neuet.</item>
               <item>Richard Barton.</item>
               <item>Iohn Braye.</item>
               <item>Thomas Cutter.</item>
               <item>Dowzabell ſkylfull in fence.</item>
               <item>Robart Egerton.</item>
               <item>Thomas Garret.</item>
               <item>Dauyd Coke.</item>
               <item>Harrye Hilles <hi>alias</hi> harry go depar.</item>
               <item>Iohn Cutter</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12796:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12796:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12796:27"/>
               <item>Folentyne Hylles his brother.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Pannell.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Morgan.</item>
               <item>Iohn Bell.</item>
               <item>Robart Bell his brother.</item>
               <item>Phillip Gréeke.</item>
               <item>Iohn Steuens.</item>
               <item>Robart Maple.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Belſon.</item>
               <item>Iohn Gray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Roba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mar.</item>
               <item>Wyliam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</item>
               <item>Iohn Why<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Thomas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewton.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Garret.</item>
               <item>Longe Gréene.</item>
               <item>Fardinand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Angell</item>
               <item>Wylliam Robynſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>Wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Vmb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruile.</item>
               <item>Iohn Rewe.</item>
               <item>Thomas W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Dauids.</item>
               <item>Iohn M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rres.</item>
               <item>Iohn a Farnando.</item>
               <item>Antony Heymer.</item>
               <item>Laurence Ladd.</item>
               <item>Dycke Glouer.</item>
               <item>Antony Iackſon.</item>
               <item>Richard Conſtans.</item>
               <item>Wyll pen</item>
               <item>Litle Iohn Gray.</item>
               <item>Robyn Bell.</item>
               <item>Thomas Grayhis toes begonne.</item>
               <item>Robbyn Topp</item>
               <item>Iohn Newman.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Iones.</item>
               <item>Great Iohn Gray.</item>
               <item>Dycke a Bryſtow.</item>
               <item>Tom Bodele.</item>
               <item>Richard Thomas.</item>
               <item>Wyll Powell.</item>
               <item>Chriſtopher Cooke.</item>
               <item>Edmund Dun a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging man.</item>
               <item>Laurence Marſhall.</item>
               <item>Richars Cadman.</item>
               <item>Edward Skinner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Shiner</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Wylliam Clark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Water Wyrrall.</item>
               <item>Ned Barington.</item>
               <item>Iohn Appconnes.</item>
               <item>Iohn Thomas.</item>
               <item>Iohn Arter.</item>
               <item>Iohn Palmer <hi>alias</hi> Todd.</item>
               <item>Iohn Goffren.</item>
               <item>Thomas Waſt.</item>
               <item>Thomas Dawſo <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</hi> Thomas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acklin.</item>
               <item>Iohn G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord.</item>
               <item>Iohn Herwod amaker of wels, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> halfe his bargaine in hand, &amp; when he hath wrought ii. or iii. daies he runneth away with his earneſt.</item>
               <item>Iohn Peter.</item>
               <item>Iohn Porter.</item>
               <item>Richard Stategood.</item>
               <item>Iohn Appowes.</item>
               <item>Harry Agglyntyne.</item>
               <item>Iohn Goddard.</item>
               <item>Edward Browne.</item>
               <item>Rychard Appryce.</item>
               <item>Harry Smith, he driue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth when he ſpeaketh.</item>
               <item>Thomas Baſet.</item>
               <item>Iohn Bates.</item>
               <item>Thomas Marchant.</item>
               <item>Thomas Web.</item>
               <item>Iohn Comes.</item>
               <item>Iohn Chyls, <hi>alias</hi> great Chylas.</item>
               <item>Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he maketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and fauſets.</item>
               <item>Iohn Loudale a may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of fence.</item>
               <item>Robart Brownſwerde, he weatenhe his heare ſongs.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Browne.</item>
               <item>Iohn Loue dale.</item>
               <item>Harry Ionſon.</item>
               <item>Water Martyn.</item>
               <item>Antony Iacſon.</item>
               <item>Robart Curſes.</item>
               <item>Thomas Awefeld.</item>
               <item>Iohn Mekes.</item>
               <item>Iohn Appowell.</item>
               <item>Thomas Gybbins.</item>
               <item>Richard Walker.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Grace.</item>
               <item>Iohn Chappell.</item>
               <item>Iohn Gryffen.</item>
               <item>Robbyn Edmundes.</item>
               <item>Thomas Lacon</item>
               <item>Richard Copar.</item>
               <item>Iohn Maſon.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12796:27"/>
               <item>Ned Wetherdon.</item>
               <item>Ned Holmes.</item>
               <item>Dauid Edwards.</item>
               <item>Wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pychering.</item>
               <item>Thomas Bate.</item>
               <item>Iohn S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ling w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſhaking head.</item>
               <item>Iohn Franke.</item>
               <item>Thomas Allen.</item>
               <item>Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ker.</item>
               <item>Dauid Holland.</item>
               <item>Iohn Baſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</item>
               <item>George Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cheſon.</item>
               <item>Dauid Iones</item>
               <item>Fraunces Dawghion.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Roges.</head>
               <item>Harry Walles with the little mouth.</item>
               <item>Iohn Waren.</item>
               <item>Richard Brewton.</item>
               <item>Thomas Haſke.</item>
               <item>Richard Horwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, wel pexe lxxx. yeres olde, he wyll byre a vi. peny nayle a ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his téeth, and a dawdy dronkard.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Carew.</item>
               <item>Iohn Donne with one legge.</item>
               <item>Iohn Elſon.</item>
               <item>Thomas Bere.</item>
               <item>Nicholas Adams a great ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amerar.</item>
               <item>Arche Dowglas a Scot.</item>
               <item>Symon Kinge.</item>
               <item>Iohn Raynoldes.</item>
               <item>Thomas Shawnean Ireſh man.</item>
               <item>Blacke Dycke</item>
               <item>George Belbar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</item>
               <item>Humfrey Warde.</item>
               <item>Lytle Robyn.</item>
               <item>Lytle Dycke.</item>
               <item>Iohn Harrys.</item>
               <item>Iames Monkaſter a counterfet Cranck,</item>
               <item>Nicholas Criſpyn.</item>
               <item>Edward Eellys.</item>
               <item>Wylliam waſtfield.</item>
               <item>Dycke Duram.</item>
               <item>Richard Crane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Kinchen co at his Backe.</item>
               <item>Nycholas Blut, <hi>alias.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nycholas Gennyns a counterfet Crank Wylſon.</item>
               <item>Godman.</item>
               <item>Iohn Dew.</item>
               <item>Iohn Crew with one arme.</item>
               <item>Nycholas Lynche.</item>
               <item>Raffe Kyteley.</item>
               <item>Richard Iones.</item>
               <item>Lambart Roſe.</item>
               <item>Harry Maſon.</item>
               <item>Thomas Smithe with the ſkal ſkyn.</item>
               <item>Dauid Dew neuet a counterfet Cranke.</item>
               <item>Iohn Browne a great ſtamerer.</item>
               <item>Edward Anſeley.</item>
               <item>Robart Harryſon.</item>
               <item>Gerard Gybbyn a counterfet Crank</item>
               <item>Wylliam Gynkes with a whyr beard a luſty and ſtronge man, he runneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the countrey to ſeke worke, with a byg boye his ſonn carying his tooles as a dawber and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterer, but lytle wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſerueth him.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Pallyards.</head>
               <item>Nycholas Newſon carieth a layned lyrence.</item>
               <item>Baſhforde.</item>
               <item>Robart Lackley.</item>
               <item>Wylliam Thomas</item>
               <item>Edward Heyward, hath his Morte following hym Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che fayneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crank Preſton.</item>
               <item>Robart Canloke.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12796:28"/>
               <item>Wylliam C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oper w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Harelyp.</item>
               <item>Thomas Edwards.</item>
               <item>Laurence with the great legge.</item>
               <item>Iohn Perſe a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet Cranke.</item>
               <item>Richard Hylton cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ii. kinchen Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes about him.</item>
               <item>Dycke S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han. Iriſh.</item>
               <item>Iohn Dauids his fellow.</item>
               <item>Wyll Penyt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reath a kinchen-morte at his back.</item>
               <item>Richard Thomas.</item>
               <item>Iohn Harriſon.</item>
               <item>Edward Lewes a dummerer.</item>
               <item>Iohn Carew.</item>
               <item>Wyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bowmet</item>
               <item>Iames Lane with one eye Iriſh.</item>
               <item>Hugh Iones.</item>
               <item>Dauid Powell.</item>
               <item>Sothegarde.</item>
               <item>Iohn Fyſher.</item>
               <item>Nycholas Decaſe.</item>
               <item>Thomas Dauids Swanders.</item>
               <item>Iohn Dewe.</item>
               <item>Dauid Iones a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt Cranke.</item>
               <item>Iohn Gylford Iriſh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a counterfet lyſence.</item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ Their is aboue an hundreth of Iriſhe men and women that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der about to begge for their lyuing, that hath come ouer within theſe twoo yeares. They laye they haue béene burned and ſpoyled by the Earele of Deſmond, and report well of the Earle of Vrmond.</p>
            <p>¶ All theſe aboue wryten for the moſt part walke about Eſſex, Myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſer, Suſſex Surrey, and Rent. Then let the reader iudge, what number walkes in other Shieres, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare me to great a number, if they be well vnderſtande.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="glossary">
            <p>HEre I ſet before thée good Reader, the leud louſey language of theſe lewtering Luſkes, and laſy Lorrels, wher with they bye and fell the common people as they paſſe through the country. Which language they terme Peddelars Frenche, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnknowen tong onely, but to theſe bold beaſtly bawdye Beggers, and vaine Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondes, being halfe myngled with Englyſhe, when it is familiarly talked, and fyrſte plaring thinges by their proper names, as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction to this peuyſh ſpéeche.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Nab. a head.</item>
               <item>Nabchet. a hat or cap.</item>
               <item>Glaſyers. eyes.</item>
               <item>a ſmeli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chete a noſe.</item>
               <item>gan. a mouth.</item>
               <item>a pratlynge chete. a tounge.</item>
               <item>Craſhinge chetes. téeth.</item>
               <item>Hearing che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. eares.</item>
               <item>fambles. handes.</item>
               <item>a famblinge chete. a rynge on thy hand.</item>
               <item>quaromes. a body</item>
               <item>prat a buttocke.</item>
               <item>ſtampes legges.</item>
               <item>a caſter a cloke.</item>
               <item>a togeman a cota.</item>
               <item>a commiſſion
<pb facs="tcp:12796:28"/> a ſhierte</item>
               <item>drawers hoſen.</item>
               <item>ſtampers ſhooes.</item>
               <item>a moflinge chete. a napkyn.</item>
               <item>a belly chete an apern.</item>
               <item>dudes clothes.</item>
               <item>a lag of duds a bucke of clothes</item>
               <item>a ſlate or ſlats a ſhéete or ſhetes</item>
               <item>lybbege a bed.</item>
               <item>bunge a purſſe.</item>
               <item>lowre money.</item>
               <item>mynt golde.</item>
               <item>a borde a ſhyllinge.</item>
               <item>halfe a borde ſixe pence.</item>
               <item>flagg a greate,</item>
               <item>a wyn a penny.</item>
               <item>a make a halfepenny,</item>
               <item>bowſe drynke.</item>
               <item>bene good</item>
               <item>benſhyp very good.</item>
               <item>quiet nouhgt.</item>
               <item>a gage a quart pot,</item>
               <item>a ſkew a cuppe.</item>
               <item>pannam bread.</item>
               <item>caſſan chéeſe.</item>
               <item>yarum mylke.</item>
               <item>lap butter, mylke, or whey.</item>
               <item>pek meate.</item>
               <item>poppelars porrage.</item>
               <item>ruff pek haken.</item>
               <item>a grunting chet or apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices kichen, a pyg.</item>
               <item>a cakli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gchet a cock or capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</item>
               <item>a margerye praier. a Hen.</item>
               <item>a Roger or tyb of the buttery a Gooſe</item>
               <item>a quakinge chet or a red ſhanke a drake or ducke</item>
               <item>grannam. corne.</item>
               <item>a lowhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chet a Cowe.</item>
               <item>a bleting chet a calfe or ſhéepe</item>
               <item>a prauncer a horſe.</item>
               <item>antem a church.</item>
               <item>Salomon a alter or maſſe.</item>
               <item>patrico a prieſt.</item>
               <item>noſegent a Nunne.</item>
               <item>a gybe a writinge.</item>
               <item>a Tarke a ſeale.</item>
               <item>a ken a houſe.</item>
               <item>a ſtauli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ken a houſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue ſtole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ware</item>
               <item>a bouſing ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ale houſe.</item>
               <item>a Lypken. a houſe to lye in</item>
               <item>a Lybbege. a bedde,</item>
               <item>glymmar, fyre.</item>
               <item>Rome bouſe wyne</item>
               <item>lage. lage. water</item>
               <item>a ſkyppar. a barne.</item>
               <item>ſtrommell. ſtrawe.</item>
               <item>a gentry cofes kenne. A noble or gentle mans houſe.</item>
               <item>a gygger, a doore.</item>
               <item>bufe. a dogge</item>
               <item>the lightmans the daye.</item>
               <item>the darkma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the night.</item>
               <item>Rome vyle London.</item>
               <item>dewſe a vile the countrey.</item>
               <item>rome morte the Qeune,</item>
               <item>a gentrye cofe a noble or gentle man.</item>
               <item>a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try mort A noble or gentle woman,</item>
               <item>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quyer cuſtyn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iuſticer of peace</item>
               <item>the harma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beck the Counſtable,</item>
               <item>the harmanes the ſtockes,</item>
               <item>Quyerken a priſon houſe,</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:12796:29"/>
               <item>Quier cramp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rings. boltes or fetters</item>
               <item>trinynge hanginge</item>
               <item>chattes the gallowes</item>
               <item>the hygh pad. the hygh waye</item>
               <item>the ruffmanes. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wods or buſhes</item>
               <item>a ſmelling chet a garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or orchard</item>
               <item>craſſinge chets apels peares or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other frute.</item>
               <item>to fyltche to beate</item>
               <item>to ſtrike to robbe.</item>
               <item>to nyp a bong. to cut a purſe</item>
               <item>To ſkowere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cramprings. to weare boltes or fetters.</item>
               <item>to heue abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh. to robbe or ryfle a boewethe.</item>
               <item>to cly the gerke to be whypped</item>
               <item>to cutte beuie. to ſpeake gentlye</item>
               <item>To cutte bene whyddes to ſpeake or gaue good words</item>
               <item>To cutte quyre whyddes. to geue euel wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or euell lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</item>
               <item>to cutte. to ſaye.</item>
               <item>to towre. to ſée</item>
               <item>to boweſe. to drynke.</item>
               <item>to maunde. to aſke or requier</item>
               <item>to ſtall. to make or ordain</item>
               <item>to cante to ſpeake.</item>
               <item>to wyll a ken to robbe a houſe.</item>
               <item>to pryggs. to ryde.</item>
               <item>to dup y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> giger to open the doore</item>
               <item>to couch a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gſheade. to ly downe ſlepe</item>
               <item>to nyggle to haue to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a woman carnally.</item>
               <item>ſtow you, a holde your peace.</item>
               <item>bynge a waſte go you hence,</item>
               <item>to the ruffian. to the deuyll</item>
               <item>the ruffian cly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the. the deuell take thée</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="sample_dialogue">
            <head>¶ The vpright Cafe canteth to the Roger </head>
            <head>The vprighte man ſpaketh to the Roge</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>Bene Lyghtmans to thy quarromes in what lipke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haſt thou lipped in this darke manes; whether in a lybbege or in the ſtrummell.</p>
               <q>God morrowe to thy bodye, in what houſe haſt thou lyue in all ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght whether in a bed, or in the ſtrawe.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roge.</speaker>
               <p>I couched a hogeſhed in a Skypper this darkemans.</p>
               <q>I laye me downe to ſléepe in a barne this night.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>I towre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrummell tryne vpon thy nabcher &amp; Tagman
<q>I ſée the ſtraw hange vpon thy cap and coate</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roge.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaye by the Salomon I wyll lage it of with a gage of bene houſe then out to my noſe watch.</p>
               <q>I ſweare by the Maſt I wyll waſh it of with a quart of drinke, then ſaye to me what thou wylt,</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>Why haſt thou any lowre in thy bonge to houſe.</p>
               <q>Why haſt thou any money in thy purfe to drinke.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roge.</speaker>
               <p>But a fiagge, a wyn and a make
<pb facs="tcp:12796:29"/>
                  <q>But a grot, a penny and a halfe penny.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>Why where is the kene that hath the bene houſe.</p>
               <q>where is the houſe that hath the good drinke.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roge.</speaker>
               <p>A bene mort hereby at the ſigne of the prauncer
<q>A good wyfe here by at the ſigne of the hors,</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>I cutt it is quyer boufe I bouſd a flagge the laſte darkemans.</p>
               <q>I ſaye it is ſmall and naughtye drynke, I dranke a groate there the laſt night.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roge.</speaker>
               <p>But bouſe there a bord &amp; thou ſhalt haue beneſhip
<q>But drinke there a ſhyllinge, and thou ſhalt haue very good.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Tower ye yander is the kene dup the gygger and maund that is beneſhype.</p>
               <q>Se you, yonder is ſhe houſe open the doore, and aſke for the beſt.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>This houſe is as benſhyp as rome bouſe.</p>
               <q>This drinke is as good as wyne.</q>
               <p>Now I to wer that bene bouſe makes naſe nabes,
<q>Now I ſo that good drynke makes a dronken heade.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Man tide of this al drie what bene pecke is in herken.</p>
               <q>Aſke of this wyfe what good meate ſhée hath in her houſe,</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roge.</speaker>
               <p>She hath a Cacling chete, a grunting chete, ruff pecke, caſſan, and popplarr of yarum.</p>
               <q>She hath a hen a pyg, baken, cheſe, and mylke porrage.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>That is beneſhyp to oure watche.</p>
               <q>That is very good for vs.</q>
               <p>Now we haue well bouſd, let vs ſtrike ſome chete
<q>Nowe we haue well dronke let vs ſteale ſome thinge.</q> yonder dwelleth a quyere cuſten it were beneſhype to myll hym.</p>
               <q>Yonder dwelleth a hoggeſhe and choprlyſhe man it weare very well donne to robbe him.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roge.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe bynge we a waſte to the hygh pad the ruff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes is by,
<q>Nays let vs go hence to the hygh waye the wodes is at hande.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>So may we happen on the Harmanes and cly the Iarke or to the quyecken and ſkower quyart tramprings and ſo to tryning on the chates.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12796:30"/>
               <q>So we maye chaunce to ſet in the ſtockes eyther be whypped ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had to priſon houſe and there be ſhackeled with bolttes and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and then to hange on the gallowes.</q>
               <p>Gerry gan the ruffian clye thee.</p>
               <q>A torde in thy mouth the deuyll take thée.</q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Man.</speaker>
               <p>What ſtowe you bene cofe and cut benar whydds and byng we to rome vyle to nyp a bong ſo ſhall we haue lowre for the bouſing ken and when we byng back to the deuſeauyel we wyll fylche ſome duddes of the Ruffemans or myll the ken for a lagge of dudes.</p>
               <q>What holde your peace good fellowe and ſpeake better wordes, and go we to London to cut a purſe, then ſhal we haue money for the ale houſe, and when wee come backe agayne into the countrey, wée wyll ſteale ſome lynnen clothes of one hedges, or robbe ſome houſe for a bucke of clothes.</q>
               <p>¶ By this lytle ye maye holy and fully vnderſtande their vntowarde talke and pelting ſpeache myngled &amp; without meaſure, and as they haue begonne of late to deuyſe ſome new termes for certien thinges: ſo wyll they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an alter this and deuyſe as euyll or worſſe. This language nowe beinge knowen and ſpred a broade, yet one thinge more I wyll ad vnto, not meaninge to Englyſh the ſame, becauſe I learned the ſame of a ſhameles Doxe, but for the phraſe of ſpeche I ſet it forth onely.</p>
               <q>There was a proude patrico and a noſegent, he tooke his Ioc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kam in his famble, and a wappinge he went, he dokte the Dell, hée pryge to praunce, he byngd a waſte into the darke mans, he fylcht the Cofe with out any fylth man.</q>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <p>WHyle this ſecond Impreſſion was in printinge it fortuned that Nycholas Blunte, who called hym ſelfe Nycholas Gennyns a counterefet Cranke, that is ſpoken of in this booke, was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de begging in the whyte fryers an New-yeres day laſt paſt Anno do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. 1567 and commytted vnto a offeſcer who caried him vnto the depetye of the ward which comytted hym vnto the counter &amp; as the counſtable and a nother would haue caried hym thether. This coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfet
<pb facs="tcp:12796:30"/> Cranke ran awaye, but one lyghter of fote then the other ouer toke hym, &amp; ſo leading him to the counter, where he remayned thrée dayes, &amp; from thence to Bryde well, where before the maiſters he had his dyſgyſed aparell put vpon hym, which was monſtrous to be holde. And after ſtode in Chepeſyde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame apparil on a ſcafold</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>A Stockes to ſtaye ſure, and ſafely detayne,</l>
               <l>Laſy lewd Leutterers, that lawes do offend,</l>
               <l>Impudent perſons, thus puniſhed with payne,</l>
               <l>Hardlye for all this, do meane to amende.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of two men each with a leg in stocks</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Fetters or ſhackels ſerue to make faſt,</l>
               <l>Male malefactours, that on myſchiefe do muſe,</l>
               <l>Vntyll the learned lawes do quite or do caſt,</l>
               <l>Such ſuttle ſearchers, as all euyll do vſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a pair of fetters or handcuffs and a pair of shackles</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:31"/>
            <lg>
               <l>A whyp is a whyſkar, that wyll wraſt out blood,</l>
               <l>Of backe and of body, beaten right well.</l>
               <l>Of all the other it doth the moſt good.</l>
               <l>Experience techeth, and they can well tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of two whips or flails and two birch-brooms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ O dolefull daye, nowe death draweth nere,</l>
               <l>Hys bytter ſtyng doth pearce me to the harte,</l>
               <l>I take my leaue of all that be here,</l>
               <l>Nowe piteouſly playing this tragicall parte,</l>
               <l>Neither ſtripes nor teachinges in tyme could conuert,</l>
               <l>wherefore an enſample let me to you be,</l>
               <l>And all that be preſent, nowe praye you for me,</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man bound at the wrists being led to a gallows past a group of people</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:31"/>
            <p>THis is the fygure of the counterfet Clarke, that is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in this boke of Roges, called Nycholas Blunt other wyſe Nycholas Gennyngs. His tale is in the xvii. lefe of this booke, which doth ſhowe vnto all that reades it, woundrous ſuttell and crafty deſeit doune of &amp; by him.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man or Nicholas Blunt or Jennings with his head imprisoned in the Counter or Compter stocks, guarded by two men armed with sticks and a third armed man nearby</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:32"/>
            <l>Thus I conclude my bolde Beggars booke,</l>
            <l>That all eſtates moſt playnely maye ſee,</l>
            <l>As in a glaſſe well pollyſhed to looke,</l>
            <l>Their double demeaner in eche degree.</l>
            <l>Their lyues their language, their names as they be,</l>
            <l>That with this warning their myndes may be warmed,</l>
            <l>To amende their myſdeedes, and ſo lyue vnharmed.</l>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the Madonna and Child or Mary and Jesus in a circular frame with roses and other flowers</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in Fleteſtrete at the ſigne of the Faulcon by Wylliam gryffith. Anno Domni. 1567. the eight of Ianuary.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12796:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
